<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno primo Edvvardi Sexti Statutes made in the Parliament begon at westminster the fowerthe daye of Nouember, in the first yeare of the reigne of the most dreade soueraine lord Edward the. VI. by the grace of God, Kinge of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the faith, and of the Churche of Englande, and also of Ireland in earthe the supreme hed: and from thence continued to the xxiiii. daye of Decembre then next ensuyng, that is to say in the first session of the same Parliament, as foloweth.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 246KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74033</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857249</idno>
  <idno type="VID">150873</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264230757</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 9421.6</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S122097</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99857249e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 62:10 or 1984:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno primo Edvvardi Sexti Statutes made in the Parliament begon at westminster the fowerthe daye of Nouember, in the first yeare of the reigne of the most dreade soueraine lord Edward the. VI. by the grace of God, Kinge of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the faith, and of the Churche of Englande, and also of Ireland in earthe the supreme hed: and from thence continued to the xxiiii. daye of Decembre then next ensuyng, that is to say in the first session of the same Parliament, as foloweth.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>vi, 7-13 [i.e. 12], xiii-xviii, 19-24, xxv-xxx, 33 [i.e. 31]-38 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Richardi Graftoni [i.e. Richard Tottell], regii impressoris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.xlviii [1548, i.e. ca. 1570?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint, from colophon, is false; actual printer's name and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Leaves 12 and 31 misnumbered 13 and 33.</note>
                  <note>In this edition title page line 5 ends "daye" in roman type.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 9418 at reel 62:10 (number changed in STC 2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: British Library and Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery .</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Law --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150873:1"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>ANNO PRIMO EDVVAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DI SEXTI.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>STATVTES <hi>made in the Parliament</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon at westminster the fower the daye</hi> of Nouember, in the first yeare of the reigne of the most dreade Soueraine lord <hi>EDWARD</hi> the <hi>.VI.</hi> By the grace of God, Kinge of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the faith, and of the Churche of Englande, and also of Ireland in earthe the supreme hed and from theme continued to the xxiiii. daye of Decembre then next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suyng, that is to say in the first Session of the same Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150873:2"/>
            <head>❧ The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Acte agaynst suche as shall vnreuerentlye</hi> speake against the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Chryst, commonly called the Sacrament of the aulter, &amp; for the rrceiuyng therof in both kindes. Chapitre. i</item>
               <item>An acte for the election of Bishoppes, &amp; what seales, &amp; stile, they, and other Spiritual persones exercisyng iurisdiccyon Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall shall vse. chapit. ii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the punishment of vagabondes, and for the reliefe of the poore and impotent persones. chap. iii.</item>
               <item>An acte for tenures holden in <hi>Capite.</hi> chap. iiii.</item>
               <item>An acte that no Horses shalbe conueighed out of this realme, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the kinges dominions without lycence. chap. v.</item>
               <item>An acte for the continuaunce of making of Woosted yarne in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke. chap. vi.</item>
               <item>An acte for the continuaunce of actions, after the death of any kyng of thys realme. chap. vii.</item>
               <item>An acte for confirmacion of letters Patentes. chap. viii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the vnytyng of certayne Churches within the Citye of Yorke. chap. ix.</item>
               <item>An acte for exigentes &amp; Proclamacions in Wales, &amp; in the Countye Palantyne of Chester, and also in the citie of Chester. chap. x.</item>
               <item>An acte for the repeale of a certaine Statute made in the .xxviii. yere of the reigne of the late kyng of most famous memorye Henrye the .viii for reuoking of actes of Parliament. chap. xi.</item>
               <item>An acte for the repeale of certain Statutes, concernynge Treasons Felonyes &amp;c. chap. xii.</item>
               <item>An acte for a Subsidie of Tonnage and poundage of Marchaundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses with a Prouiso, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> confirmacion of the Priuileges of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes of the Stilliarde, whiche Prouiso shall endure but onelye to the ende of this Parliament. chap. xiii.</item>
               <item>An Acte whereby certaine Chauntries, Colleges, free Chapelles, &amp; the possessions of the same be geuen to the Kinges Maiesty. chap. xiiii.</item>
               <item>An acte for a general pardon. chap. xv.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:150873:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>An Acte against suche persons as shall vnreuerentlye <hi>speake against the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Christe,</hi>
               </hi> commonly called the Sacrament of the Aulter: &amp; for the receiuyng therof vnder both kindes. ¶ The first Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Kinges moste excellent Maiesty minding the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernaunce &amp; order of his most louing subiects to be in moste perfite vnitie and concord, in al thinges, &amp; in es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecial, in the true faith &amp; Religion of God, &amp; wishinge the same to be brought to passe with all clemency and mercy, on his highnesse parte towardes them, as his moste Princely serenity &amp; Maiestye hath alreadye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by euident proufe to thintent that hys most louing subiects pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked by clemency &amp; goodnesse of their Prince &amp; kyng, shall studye ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for loue, thē for feare to doe theire duties, first to almighty God, &amp; then to his highnesse &amp; the common wealth, nourishyng concord &amp; loue emong them selues: yet cōsidereth &amp; perceyueth that in a multitude al bee not on that sort, that reason and the knowledge of their duityes cā moue them from offence, but many, which had neede haue some bridle of feare, &amp; that the same be men moste contencious &amp; arrogante for the moste parte, or elles most blinde &amp; ignoraunt: by the meanes of whych sort of men, many things well &amp; godlye instituted, &amp; to the dificacion of many, be peruerted &amp; abused, &amp; turned to their own &amp; others gret losse &amp; hinderaunce, &amp; some time to extreme destruccion: the which doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in nothing more or soner, then in matters of Religion, and in the great &amp; high misteries therof, as in the moste comfortable Sacrament of the body &amp; bloud of our sauiour Iesus Christe, commonly called the Sacramente of the Aulter, and in scripture, the<note n="‡" place="margin">i. Cor. 11.</note> Supper and<note n="*" place="margin">i. Cor. 8</note> Table of the Lord, the<note n="‡" place="margin">i. Cor. 10.</note> Communion<note n="*" place="margin">i. Cor. 10.</note> and partaking of the body and bloud of Christe: which Sacrament was instituted of no lesse aucthor, then of our Sauiour, both God &amp; man, when at his last supper emongst his Apostles he did take y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bread into his holy hands, &amp; did say<note n="‡" place="margin">Math. 26.</note>
               <hi>Take you &amp; eate, this is my body, which is</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke. 22</note>
               <hi>geuen &amp;</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">i. Cor. 11</note>
               <hi>broken for you.</hi> And taking vp y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Math. 26. Marke. 14.</note> chalice or cup, did<note n="‡" place="margin">Marke. 14</note> geue thāks &amp; say, <hi>This is my bloud of the newe testamēt, which is shed for you</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke. 21</note>
               <hi>&amp; for</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Marke. 14</note>
               <hi>many, for the remission of sinnes,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">i. Cor. 11</note> whensoeuer we should do y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, we should do it in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> remēbrāce of him, &amp; to declare &amp; set forth his death &amp; most glorious passiō, vntil his cōming. Of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 26</note> bread, whosoeuer eateth, or of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which cup who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer drynketh vnworthely, eateth &amp; drinketh condēpnacion &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him selfe, making no difference of the Lordes body.<note n="‡" place="margin">i. Cor. 11</note> The insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion of which Sacramente being ordeyned by Chryste,<note n="*" place="margin">i. Cor. 11.</note> as is before said, and the saide woordes spoken of it here before rehearsed, being of eternal, infallible, &amp; vndoubted trueth: yet the said Sacramēt (al this notwithstanding) hath been of late merueilously abused by suche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:150873:3"/> of men before rehearsed, who of wickednesse, or els of ignoraunce &amp; want of learning for certein abuses, heretofore, committed of some, in misusing therof, haue condempned in their hartes and speche, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole thing, and contempteously depraued, despised, or reuiled the same most holy and blessed Sacrament, and not onely disputed &amp; reasoned vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently and vngodly of that most high misterye, but also in theire ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: preachinges, readinges, lectures, communicacions, arguments, talkes, runes, songes, plaies, or gestes, name, or call it by suche vile and vnsemely woordes, as Christian eares doe abhorre to heare rehersed: for reformacion whereof be it enacted by the Kings highnesse with the assent of the Lordes spirytual and temporall, &amp; of the commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by the aucthority of the same, that whatsoeuer persone or persons, from, and after the first daye of Maye next comming, shall depraue, despise or contemne the saide most blessed Sacrament, in contempt thereof by any contempteous woords, or by any wordes of deprauing, despising, or reuiling: or what person, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, shal aduisedsy in any otherwise contemne, despise, or reuile y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saide most blessed Sacrament, contrary to the effectes, &amp; declaracion aboue saide, that then he, or they, shall suffer imprisonment, of his, or their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies &amp; make fine &amp; raunsome at the kinges wil &amp; pleasure.</p>
            <p>And for full and effectual execucion of the premisses before deuysed, ordeined and enacted by this act: be it furthermore enacted by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of this present Parliament, that immediatly after the first day of May next comming, the Iustices of peace, or three of them at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> least wherof one of them to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> in euery shire of this Realme and Wales, and al other places within the kings dominions, shal haue ful power and aucthoritie by vertue of this act, aswel to take informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and accusacion by thothes and deposicions of twoe able, honest, &amp; leful persons at the least, and after suche accusacion, or informacion so had to enquire by the othes of .xii. men, in euery their .iiii. quarter sessy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons yerely to be holden, of al and singuler such accusacions, or informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions to be had, or made of any of the offences abouesaid, to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or done after the saide first day of May, within the limits of theire commission: and that vpon euery such accusacion and informacion, the offendour, and offendours shalbe inquired of, &amp; indicted before the said Iustices of peace, or three of thē at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> least, as is aforesaid, of the said cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes and offences, by the verdict of .xii. honest, and indifferent men if the matter of the said accusacion &amp; informacion shal seme to the saide Iury good and true.</p>
            <p>And it is also further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that the saide Iustices of peace, or three of them at the least, as is aforesaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom any suche presentment, informacion, and accusacion shall be made, or taken, as is aforesaide, shall examine the accusors, what other witnesse were by, and present at the time of the doing and committing
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:150873:3"/> of thoffence: wherof the informacion, accusacion, &amp; presentment shalbe made, and how many others then the accusors, haue knowledge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and shal haue power and aucthoritie, by their diserecions, to bind by recognisaunce to be taken before them aswell the said accusours, as all suche other persones, whom the same accusoures shall declare to haue knowlege of the offences by them presented &amp; informed euery of them in fiue poundes to the king, to appeare before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said Iustices of peace before whom the offendour, or offendors shalbe tried at the day of trial and delyuerance of suche offendours.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayd, that the sayd Iustices of Peace, or three of them at the least, as is abouesaid, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this acte, shall haue full power and aucthorytie to make processe agaynste euerye persone &amp; persones so indicted by two <hi>Capias</hi> &amp; an exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and by <hi>Capias vtlagat{ur},</hi> aswell within the lymyttes of their cōmissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as into al other Shieres &amp; places of this realme, Wales, and other the Kinges dominions, aswel wythin the libertyes as withoute, &amp; the same processe to be good and effectual in the law to al intents, construc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and purposes, &amp; vppon the apparaunce of any of the offendours, shall haue full power &amp; aucthoritye by vertue of this acte, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missyon of peace, to determyne the contemptes and offences aforesaid, accordyng to the lawes of this Realme, and effectes of thys acte: and that the said Iustices of peace, or three of them at the least, as is aboue sayd, shall haue full power and aucthoritye to let anye suche persone, or persones so indicted, vppon suffycyent suerties, by their discrecions, to baile, for their apparaunce to be tried, according to the tenour, fourme, &amp; effect of thys acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted, that the said Iustices of peace or three of them at the least, at their quarter Sessions, where any offē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour or offendours shalbe, or stande indicted of any of the contemptes, or offences abouesaide, shall directe &amp; awarde one write in the kinges name to the Bishop of the Diocese, wherin the sayde offence or offēces are supposed to be committed, or done willynge and requiring the said Bishop to be in his owne persone, or by his Chauncellour, or other his suffycient deputye learned, at the quarter Sessions in the said County to ve holden when, &amp; where the saide offendour shalbee arreigned and tried, appointing to them in the sayd writ the day and place of the sayd arraignement, whiche write shalbe of this fourme: <hi>Rex &amp;c. Ep̄o L. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem. Praecipimus tibi, quod tu, Cancellarius tuus, vel alius Deputatus tuus sufficient{ur} eruditus, sitis cum Iusticiarijs nostris ad pacem in com̄ nr̄o B. conseruand assignat{ur} apud D. tali die, ad Sessionem nostram, ad tunc &amp; ibm̄ tenend' and dand' consiliū &amp; aduisament' eisdem Iusticiarijs nostris ad pacē super arrainment &amp; deliberationem offendent' contra formā statuti, cōcernen̄ sacro sanctum Sacramentum Altatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and bee it enacted by the aucthority abouesaide
<pb facs="tcp:150873:4"/> that no persone or persones shalbe indicted of any of the contempts, or offences abouesayd, but onely of such contempts, or offences, as shal be doone, or perpetrated within three monethes, next after the said offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or offence so committed or done.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthority aforesaide, that in al tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alles for any suche offendours before the saide Iustices, as is aforesaid the persone or persones being complaind on and arraigned, shall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to purge or trie his, or their innocencie, by as many, or moe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses in number &amp; of as good honestye and credence, as the witnesses be, whiche deposed against him, or any of them.</p>
            <p>And for asmuche as it is more agreable, both to the first instytucyon of the saide Sacrament, of the moste precious bodye and bloud of our Sauiour Iesus Christ, and also more conformable to the common vse and practise both of the Apostles, and of the primatiue Churche, by the space of fiue hundreth yeres, and more, after Christs ascention, that the saide blessed Sacrament should be ministred to al Christyan people vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der bothe the kyndes of bread &amp; wine, then vnder the fourme of bread onely: and also it is more agreable to the first institucion of Christ, and to the vsage of the Apostles, and the primatiue church, that the people being present should receiue the same with the Priest, then y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Priest should receiue it alone: therfore be it enacted by our Soueraine Lorde the Kyng with the consent of the lordes Spirytuall &amp; Temporall, and the commons in thys present Parlyamente assembled, and by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the same, that the saide moste blessed Sacrament be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cōmonly deliuered, &amp; ministred vnto the people, within this churche of England and Ireland, &amp; other the Kinges dominyons vnder bothe the kynds, that is to say, of bread and wine, except necessitie otherwise require: and also that the Priest, whiche shall minister the same, shall at the least one day before exhort al persones, whiche shalbe present, lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to resorte and prepare themselues to receiue the same. And when the day prefixed cometh, after a godly exhortaciō by the minister made (wherein shalbe further expressed the benefite and comforte promysed to them, whiche worthely receiue the holye Sacrament, and daunger and indignacion of God threatned to them, whiche shall presume to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the same vnworthely, to the ende that euery manne may trie and examine his owne conscience before he shal receiue the same) the sayde minister shal not without a lawful cause denie the same to any persone, that wil deuoutly and humbly desire it: any lawe, statute, ordinaunce, or custome contrary thereunto in any wise notwithstandinge, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempning hereby the vsage of any churche oute of the kynges Maies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties dominions.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte for the election of Bishoppes, and what Seales and stile they, and other Spiritual persons exercising iurisdiccion Ecclesiastical shal vse.
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:150873:4"/> ¶ The .ii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche as the eleccyon of the Archebyshoppes and Bys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppes by the Deanes and Chapiters, within the Kynges Maiesties Realmes of Englande and Irelande, at thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent tyme, be aswell to the longe delaye, as to the great costes and charges of suche persons, as the Kings Maiestie geueth any Archebishoprich, or Bishopriche vnto: and whereas the sayde elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be in very deede no elections, but onely by a writte of <hi>Conge des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> haue coloures, shadowes or pretences of elections, seruinge neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse to no purpose, &amp; seming also derogatorye and preiudicial to the kynges prerogatiue roial, to whom onelye apperteinethe the collacyon and gifte of all Archebishopriches, and Bishopriches, and Suffragain Bishoppes, within his highnesse saide Realmes of England, and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Wales, and other his dominions and Marches: For a due refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion hereof, be it therefore enacted by the Kinges highnes with the assent of the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and the Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by aucthoritie of the same, that from henceforth, no such <hi>Conge deslier</hi> be graunted, nor election of any Archebyshoppe or Bishoppe, by the Deane and Chapiter made: But that the kyng may by his letters Patents at al times, when any Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishopriche, or Bishopriche be voide, conferre the same to anye persone whom the king shall thinke meete. The whiche collacion so by the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges letters Patentes made, and deliuered to the person, to whom the king shall conferre the same Archebishoprich or Bishopriche, or to hys sufficient Proctour, and Attourney, shall stande to al intents, construc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and purposes, to asmuche and the same effecte, as though <hi>Conge deslier</hi> had ben geuen, the election duely made, and the same cōfirmed: and that vpon the saide persone, to whom the sayde Archebishoprich, Bishoprich, or Suffraganshippe is so conferred, collated, or geuen, may be consecrated, and sue his liuerie, or <hi>ouster le maine,</hi> and do other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aswell, as if the saide ceremonies and elections had beene doone &amp; made.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by aucthoritie aforesaid, that euery suche persone, to whom any collacion, or gift of any Archebishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riche, Bishopriche, or Suffraganshippe shalbe geuen or collated by the king, his heires, or successours, shal pay, doe, and yelde to all and euery persone, all suche fees, interestes, and duties, as of olde time haue been accustomed to bee done: any thing in this act, or in any other, to the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereof, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And where as the Archebishoppes and Bishoppes, and other Spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual persons in this Realme dooe vse to make &amp; sende out their som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, citacions, and other processe in theire owne names, and in suche fourme and maner, as was vsed in the tyme of the vsurped power of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Bishop of Rome, contrary to the fourme and order of the sommōs and
<pb facs="tcp:150873:5"/> processe of the common lawe vsed in this realme: seeing that al auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Iurisdiccion, Spiritual and temporal, is deriued and deducted from the Kinges Maiestie, as supreme head of these Churches &amp; Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of Englande, and Ireland, and so iustly acknowleged by the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the saide Realmes, &amp; that al courts ecclesiasticall, within the said twoe Realmes bee kepte by noe other power, or aucthoritie eyther fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyne, or wythin the Realme, but by the aucthorytie of hys moste ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maiestie: Bee it therefore further enacted by the aucthoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, that al somons &amp; citacions, or other processe ecclesiastical, in al suites and causes of instaunce, betwixt partie &amp; party, and all causes of correction, and al causes of bastardie, or begamie, or inquirie <hi>de Iure Patronatus,</hi> probates of testamentes, and commissions of administraciō of persones deceassed, and all acquitaunces, of, and vppon accomptes made by the executours, administratrours, or collectours of goods of any ded persone, be from the firste day of Iuly nexte folowing made in the name, and with the stile of the king, as it is in writtes origynall, or iudicial at the common lawe: and that the <hi>teste</hi> therof be in the name of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Archbishop or Bishop, or other hauing Ecclesiastical iurisdiccion who hath the commission and graunt of the aucthority Ecclesiastical, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly from the Kinges highnesse, and that his commissary, officiall, or substitute exercising iurisdiccion vnder him, shal put his name in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, or processe after the <hi>teste.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, be it enacted by aucthoritie aforesaide, that all maner of person or persons, who hath the exercise of Ecclesiasticall iurisdicciō shall haue from the first day of Iuly before expressed, in theire seales of Office, the Kinges highnesse armes decently sette with certain carects vnder the armes, for the knowledge of the Diocese: and shal vse no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther seale of iurisdiccion, but wherin his Maiesties armes be engrauē vppon pein that if any person shall vse Ecclesiastical iurisdiccyon (after the day before expressed) in this Realme of England, wales, and other his dominions, or territories, and not sende, or make out the Citacion, or processe in the kyngs name, or vse any seale of iurisdiccion, other thē before limitted that euery suche offendoure shall incurre, &amp; runne in the Kinges Maiesties displeasure, &amp; indignacion, and suffre imprisonment at his highnesse will &amp; pleasure.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that no more, nor other fees be taken, or paid for the Seale &amp; writting of any Citacions, or other processe, thē was here tofore accustomed.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and bee it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that the Archebishoppe of Cantorbury for the time being, shal vse his owne seale, and in his owne name, in al faculties and dispensacion, according to the tenour of an acte therof made: and that the sayde Archebishops and Bishoppes shall make, admitte, order, and refourme their Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, Officialles, Commissaries, Aduocates, Proctours, and other
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:150873:5"/> their offycers, ministers, &amp; substitutes, &amp; commissyons to Suffragaine Bishoppes in their owne names, vnder their own seales, in such maner &amp; fourme, as they haue heretofore vsed: &amp; shal certify to the Courte of Tenthes, their certificats vnder their owne names &amp; seales, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue vsed, &amp; accordinge to the statute in that case made &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded: &amp; likewise shall make collacions, presentacions, giftes, instituci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; inductions of benefites, letters or orders, or dimissories, vnder their owne names &amp; seales, as they haue heretofore accustomed: anye thing in this act conteyned to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, &amp; be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that al processe hereafter to be made, or awarded by any Ecclesiastical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons, for the triall of any plea, or pleas, or matter depending, or that hereafter shal depend in any of the kings courts of Recorde, at the common lawe, &amp; limitted by the lawes &amp; customes of this realme, to the spiritual courtes to trie the same: that the certificat of the same, after the trial therof shalbe made in the kings name, for the time being and with the stile of rhe same kyng, and vnder the seale of the Bishop, grauen with the kings armes, with the name of the Bishop, or spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all officer beinge to the <hi>teste</hi> of the same processe and certificat, and to euery of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .iii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte for the punishing of vagaboundes, &amp; for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the poore and impotent persons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuche, as idlenesse and vagabondry, is the mother and roote of all theftes, robberyes, and all euill actes, and other mischiefes, and the multitude of people geuen thereto hathe alwaies bene here within this Realme very great, and more in number (as it maye appeare) then in other Regions, to the great impouerishment of the Realme, and daunger of the kings high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse subiectes: the which idlenesse &amp; vagaboundry al the kyngs high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse noble progenitours, kinges of this realme, and thys high courte of parliament hath often and with great trauaile, gon about &amp; assayed with godly actes &amp; statutes, to represse, yet vntill this our time, it hath not had that successe, which hath bene wished, but partly by folishe py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and mercy of them, which should haue sene the saide godly laws ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, partly by the peruerse nature, and long accustomed idlenes of the persons geuen to loitering, the saide godly statutes hetherto hathe had small effecte, and idle and vagabonde persons, being vnprofitable members, or rather enemies of the common wealth, hath bene suffered to remain and increase, and yet so do whom, if they should be punished by death, whipping, imprisonmente, and with other corporal paine, it were not without their desertes for the example of others, and to the benefite of the cōmon wealth: yet if they could be brought to be made profitable, and doe seruyce, it were muche to bee wished and desired:
<pb facs="tcp:150873:6"/> Be it therefore enacted by the kynges highnes, with the consent of the Lordes Spiritual &amp; temporal, &amp; the commons in this present Parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment assembled, &amp; by aucthoritie of the same, first that all statutes and actes of parliament heretofore made for the punishment of vagabonds &amp; sturdy beggers, &amp; all articles comprised in the same, shalbe frō hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth repealed, voide &amp; of none effect.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that whosoeuer, after the first daye of Aprill nexte follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, man, or woman being not lame, impotent, or so aged, or diseased with sicknesse, that he, or she cannot woorke, not hauing lands, or tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, fees, annuities, or any other yerely reuenues, or profits where on they may finde sufficiently their liuing, shal, eyther like a seruing mā wanting a Master, or like a begger, or after anye suche other sorte, bee lurking in any house, or houses, or loytering, or idly wander by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies side, or in stretes, in cities, townes, or villages, not applying thē selfe to some honest, and allowed arte, science, seruice, or labour, and so do continue by the space of three daies, or more together, and not offer them selues to labour with any that wil take them, according to theire faculty: &amp; if no man, otherwise will take them, do not offre themselues to woorke for meate and drinke, or after they be so taken to worke, for the space agreed betwixt them &amp; their master, doe leaue theire woorke out of conuenient time, or run away: that then euery such persone shall be taken for a vagabounde, and that it shalbe lawful to euery such ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster offring such idle persone seruice, and labour, and that being by him refused, or who hathe agreed wyth suche idle persone, and from whom within the space agreed of seruice, the said loyterer hath rūne away, or departed before the end of the couenaunt betwene them, and to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther person espying the same to bring, or cause to be brought the sayde persone so liuing idly, and loyteringly, to two of the nexte Iustices of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Peace there resiaunt, or abiding, who hearing the proufe of the idle ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of the said persone by the saide space liuing idly, as is aforesaid, approued to them by two honest witnesses, or confession of the partye, shall immediatly cause the saide loiterer to be marked with an hoat I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron in the breast, the marke of <hi>V.</hi> and adiudge the saide persone liuinge so idly to suche presentour, to be his slaue: to haue and to holde the said slaue to him, his executours, or assignes for the space of two yeres then next folowing, and to order the saide slaue, as foloweth: that is to say to take suche persone adiudged a slaue with him, and onely geuing the saide slaue bread and water, or small drinke, and such refuse of meat as he shal thinke mete, cause the saide slaue to woorke by beatinge, chey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or otherwise, in suche woorke and labour (how vile soeuer it be) as he shall put him vnto. And if any maner of slaue, eyther for loitering or for the cause before rehersed so adiuged, shal within the space of the sayde two yeares here appointed runne awaye, departe, or absente him from his said master, by the space of .xiiii. daies together, without
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:150873:6"/> licence: It shal not onely be lefull to his said Maister to pursue &amp; serch him again by vertue of this acte, but also to punishe such fault by chey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or beating, as is aforesaide: and against the deteinour, if any man doe wyllynglye deteine him, knowing him to be a slaue, as is aforesaid to haue an action of trespasse, and recouer thereby in damages tenne poundes, besides the costs and charges of the suite for so deteyning his saide slaue. And further, euery such master shewing, &amp; prouyng by two suffycient witnesses, the saide offence and faulte of hys runnyng away before twoe Iustices of Peace of the same Countye, whereof the one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> the same Iustyces shal cause suche slaue, or loyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to be marked on the forehed, or the balle of the cheke with an hoate Iron, with the signe of an <hi>S.</hi> that he may be knowen for a loyterer, and a runne awaye, and shal adiuge the loyterer, and runne away to be the saide Masters slaue for euer. And if suche slaue shall the seconde tyme runne away, or absent him selfe. if the saide Master shall approue the same seconde runnyng awaye, with twoe sufficient witnesses before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iustice of peace, in their general and quarter sessyons: then euery suche faulte and running away to be adiudged felony, and such loytererer &amp; runne away to be taken as a felon, and therof being lawfully indicted and attainted, or otherwise condempned to suffer peines of deathe, as other felons ought to doe.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and bee it enacted by aucthoritie aforesaide, that no clerke conuicted shall hereafter make his purgacion, &amp; vppon such pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion be deliuered, and set at large otherwise then is in the Statute hereafter expressed.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by auctoritie aforesaide that euerye clerke conuict, or hereafter to be conuicted, whych should by the order of the lawe enioye the benefite of their purgacion, shall and may from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth finde any man (if they can) who shall be bound with two suffycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent suerties to the ordinary, in the summe of .xx. li. to the kings highnes vse, to retaine the said conuict as his slaue, and, to kepe the sayd person so conuicte for the space of one yere then next folowing, that he shal not goe abroade, and at large, and then the said conuicte shal bee deliuered to the saide persone so taking the same, &amp; being bound, as is aforesaid, to be his slaue for one whole yere then next folowing by vertue of this acte, in all such maner and fourme, and to all suche intentes and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and with all such order lawes, condicions, &amp; penalties for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iuining away, or other, as is aforesaid of a vagabonde, taken loitering &amp; made a slaue (burning in the breast onely except:) &amp; the ordinarye by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery of the saide conuicte to such person being bound, as is aforesaid to be of the keping of the saide conuict clerely discharged, and exonera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by vertue of this acte.</p>
            <p>And if so be that the saide clerke so conuicte cannot finde anye man to be bounde, as is aforesaide, to whom he may be adiudged a slaue in
<pb facs="tcp:150873:7"/> the space of one yere: then at any time after thend of one yere, after his conuiction, it shalbe lawful for the said Clerke conuict to make his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion, as he might before this estatute, any thing in this presente acte to the contrary notwithstandyng.</p>
            <p>And where the Clarkes conuicted, or atteynted by the order of the lawes of thys Realme, cannot make their purgacion, and should perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually by the same remayne in prison, bee it neuerthelesse enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that if there be any maner of person, who wil at any time demaund the same clerke conuicted, or attaynted, &amp; be bound to the ordinary with two sufficient suerties, as is aboue writtē, to kepe the same as his slaue, by the space of fiue yeres then next folowing, that then the same shalbe adiudged his slaue for like space, with al such or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, lawes, and penalties, for running awaye, and other orders, as is before expressed of a vacabounde adiudged to any man for a slaue (the burning in the breast onely except) &amp;. vpon the adiudgement deliuered to suche demaundaunt, thordinarye from thenceforth of the keping of such Clerke conuicted, or attainted, clerely exonerated, and discharged by vertue of this acte.</p>
            <p>And forasmuch as diuers women and men goeth on begging way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairing, of the which some be impotent and lame, and some able enough to labour, whiche doe carye children about with them, some .iiii. or .v. yeres of age, or yonger, or elder, whiche brought vp in idlenesse might be so roted in it, that hardely they may be brought after to good thrifte and labor: or if any childe aboue the age of fiue yeres, &amp; vnder the age of .xiiii. yeres go idlye wandring about as a vagabonde: be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that if any maner of person will take any such childe, bee it male, or female, of, and from any suche begger beinge the mother therof, nourisher or keper, whether they bee willing or not, or without any suche norice, mother or keper by him selfe wandering, and bring the saide childe so taken away before one of the Constables of the parishe, and two other honeste, and discrete neighbors witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and before any Iustice of peace there resiaunt, and abydinge, and promesse to bring the same childe vp in some honest labor, or occupaciō til he or she come to the age of .xx. yeres the woman childe. or .xxiiii. the man childe: that then and immediatly the saide Iustice of Peace &amp; Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable shal adiudge by vertue of this acte, the said child vnto the ages before specified, to be seruauntes or apprentices to the saide persons so taking and promising to be vsed and ordered in all pointes accordinge as the lawe and custome of this Realme is of seruauntes and apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to what labour occupation, or seruice soeuer the saide Master shal appointe him, or her, during the saide time. And if it shall fortune suche childe so adiudged to runne away at any time, once, or moe times, from his or her master, or mastres: that then it shalbe lawful for euery suche Maister, to take the saide childe again, and to kepe and punish the said
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150873:7"/> chylde, in cheynes or otherwise, and vse him, or her, as hys slaue in all pointes, for the tyme before rehearsed, of the age of suche chylde, that is to say, till twentie the woman childe, and the man childe .xxiiii.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that any maister, eyther of the men, or of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men so adiudged slaues, or of the children adiudged apprentices or ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, may lette, set forth, sel, bequeathe, or geue the seruice &amp; labor of suche slaues or seruauntes so adiudged, as is aforesayde, to any persone, or persones, to whomsoeuer he will, vpon suche condition, and for suche tyme of yeres as the saide persones bee adiudged to him for slaues, ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, or apprentices, after suche like sorte and maner, as he may do of any other his moueable goodes or cattalles: and they for the said spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and time, to be bound to all poinctes and constructions to such <hi>lessee, donee, vendee, or assignee,</hi> as they were to theire first apprehenders and maisters, by vertue of this statute.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; bee it enacted by aucthoritie aforesayde: that if any such slaue, or slaues, or children so adiudged, shall at any tyme after suche adiudgement, mayme, or wounde theire maisters or mistresses, in resisting theire correction, or otherwise: or when they be Manumitted, &amp; set agayne free, or in the tyme of their seruice, shall conspire with anye other, or by themselues go about to murder &amp; kyl, or to maime, wounde, or beate the said maister or maistresse, or any that was theire maister or maistresse, or to burne their houses, barnes, or corne, so that their entent come to an acte tending to the effecte: that then euerye suche maime, or wounde, or the going about to murder, kill, maime, wounde, or beate suche persone or persones, as bee, or were theire maister or mistressesses, or to burne their houses, barnes, or corne, so that their entent do come to any acte tending to the same effecte, as lying in wayte with weapon, or anye suche like, shalbe accompted Felonye, and they shal suffer therefore peines of death, as in case of Felonie: excepte that anye suche persone or persones as be, or had been maister or maistresse to any of them, or he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing any other wil take suche person so offending, to theire slaues, and thē he or she so offending to be adiudged to the person so willing to take him or her so offending slaue for euer, and therupon to be discharged of the felonie. The same lawe and ordre to be had in all cōditiōs, if it should chaūce the father, mother, nourice, or other the bearer about of the child or any other persone, or persones, to steale away suche childe adiudged apprentice or seruaunt, that is, to bee slaue to suche apprentices, or ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes maister, whose apprentice or seruaunt was so stolen or entised awaie, for euer: &amp; the maister neuertheles to take &amp; receiue his said ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prētice or seruaūt again, as if the said taking awaie had neuer be doen.</p>
            <p>Bee it also enacted by aucthoritie aforesaid, that although there be no man which shall demaūde such loiterer, or loiterers, as before expressed into theire seruice, yet neuerthelesse the Iustice of peace in that citie, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe, towne, or hundred dwelling, if anye suche bee, or els anye other
<pb facs="tcp:150873:8"/> Iustice of peace of the same Shyre, and also there dwellinge, by hys, or theire office shalbe hereafter bounde by vertue of thys acte, not onely to enquire of all suche ydle persones, but also if they doe espye anye suche vagabondes, or ydle persone, or if anye suche bee detected vnto them, to examine him, or her, of the tyme of theyr vagaboundrye: and if it shall appeare to any Iustice of peace, any suche man or woman to haue been a vagraunt and vagabound, or ydle person, by the space as is aforesaid, to cause the same to bee marked on the breste with an. <hi>V.</hi> made with an hoate yron, and also to learne and enquire of hym the Towne, Citie, or village, wherein hee was borne, and then shall immediately geue a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in parchement sealed with hys seale, to the sayd loyterer, of the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; fourme, which here ensueth. ¶ <hi>A.B.</hi> Iustice of peace in the coūtie of <hi>S.</hi> to the Maiour, or chiefe officer of the citie of. <hi>Q.</hi> (if it be a Citye, or to the head borough, Baylife, or Constable, or head officer of the towne of Q. (if it bee a Towne) or to the Constable, or Tything man of the Village of C. (if it be a village) greting: According to a moste, godlye Statute made in the first yere of the reigne of our Souereigne Lorde kyng Edwarde the sixte &amp;c. we haue taken thys bearer. <hi>I.K.,</hi> vagraunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and to the euill example of others, without maister, seruice, or labor whereby to gette hys liuing, going loitering idlye aboute. And because the same sayth, he was borne in C. in the countie of S. wherof you are the head officer or Constable. We haue sent hym to you to be ordred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the purporte and effect of the same Statute. And with thys writing shall deliuer the same loyterer to the Constables, or other head officer of the said Citie, Towne, or Village, wherein suche loyterer was taken, to be safely conueighed by them to the nexte Constable, &amp; so from Constable to Constables, &amp; other head officers, till he or she be brought to the place, the whiche, he or she, hath named them selfe to bee borne in, and then to bee deliuered to the heade officer or Constable of that same Citie, Borough, or Towne, Village, Hamlette, or Paryshe, there to bee nourished and kept of the same Citie. Towne, or Village, in cheynes, or otherwise, either at the common workes, in amending hyghe wayes, or other common worke, or from man to man in order, till they which may beare be equally charged to be slaue to the corporation of the citie, or to the inhabitauntes of the towne or village, that he or she were borne in, after all suche fourme, condition, space of yeres, ordres, punishments for running away, &amp; all others, as are expressed of a commō or priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone to whom any such loiterer is adiudged a slaue. And the sayde citie, Towne, or village shall see the sayde slaue beyng able to labour, sette on worke, &amp; not liue idlye within the said precinctes, vpon paine for euerye suche defaulte, that the sayde slaue doth lyue ydly, by the defaulte of the Citie, borough, or towne, or village, by the space of thre working dayes together, the citie of forfeite .v. li. a Borough, or towne incorporate xl. s. and other towne or village .xx.s. whereof the one halfe to the kyng our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150873:8"/> soueraigne lord, the other to him that will sue for the same, in any of the kynges courtes of Record, by bill, information, or action of debte, in the which suites, no essoine, wager of lawe, or protection shalbe allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided and be it enacted, that the Citie, Towne, and borough cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, by the consent of the more parte of the corporation: &amp; the towne and village not corporate, by the consent of the more parte of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tauntes thereof, may sette, sell, or geue awaye the righte, title, &amp; interest of the saide slaue, to anye other person, as any other common or priuate persone may do with hys slaue, by the vertue of thys Acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted, that if it fortune when the saide vacabonde is brought to the sayde Citie, Towne, or village, where the said persone said he was borne, to appeare, &amp; be manifest, that he, or shee was not there borne: that then for suche lye, the saide vagaraunt shalbe marked in the face with an. <hi>S.</hi> and be slaue to the inhabitauntes, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration of the Citie, Towne, or village, where the saide vagaraunte sayde he was borne in, for euer, vpon such conditions, and orders, in all poynctes, as of a slaue marked in the face is before expressed: the same lawe, and order in all poinctes to be had of all vagaraunt persones, and vagabondes beinge borne in anye other nation or countreye, then thys Realme, as is before expressed of Englishe ydle persones, (markinge in the breast or face onely excepted) that is, to be had to the next porte, and there to be kepte of the inhabitauntes of the sayde nexte port, in conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient labour, and from ydlenesse, or otherwise, till they may be conueyed ouer: and then at the costes of the inhabitauntes of the sayd porte, to be conueighed ouer into their countreyes.</p>
            <p>And forasmuche as there is manye maymed, &amp; otherwise lamed, sore aged, &amp; impotent persones, which resorteth to the citie of London, &amp; to other cities, townes, &amp; villages, on begging: whose coming together, &amp; makinge a number, doth fill the streetes or high wayes of diuers cities, townes, markettes &amp; fayres, who, if they wer seperated, mought easely be nourished in the townes &amp; places wherin they were borne, or where they were, or haue been most conuersaunt and abidinge, by the space of three yeres: Be it therfore enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that all &amp; singuler Mayours, Shirifes, Baylifes, Constables, or other head of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of any citie, towne, or hundred, to whiche suche resorte is, or shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, shal before the feast of the Purification of our Lady next folowing, see all such ydle, impotent, maymed, &amp; aged persones, who otherwise can not by their discretions bee taken for vagabondes, whiche were borne within the said citie, towne, or Hundrede, or hath been there moste con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaunt and abiding by the space of three yeres as is aforesaid, &amp; now decayed, bestowed, and prouided for of Tenantries, Cotages, or other conuenient houses, to bee lodged in, at the costes &amp; charges of the sayde Cities, townes, boroughes, and villages, there to be releued and cured by the deuotion of the good people of the said Citie, borough, towne, or
<pb facs="tcp:150873:9"/> village. And that they doe not suffer after the time before rehersed, any other then suche as eyther were borne, or hathe been for the most parte conuersaunt or abiding, by the space aforesayde, in the sayde Citie, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe, Village, or Towne, to remaine and begge abroade within the precinctes of such Cities, Townes, villages, or Hundredes: vpon peine that euerye such Maiours, Shirifes, and Baylifes, Constable, or other head officer, by what name so euer he be called suffering any persones to begge within the precincte of hys or theire suche iurisdiction, other then is before rehearsed, for euery three dayes shal forfait x.s. to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer will sue therfore, by byll, information, or action of debte, in anye Courte of Recorde, in the whiche suites, no essoyne, wager of lawe, nor protection shalbe allowed.</p>
            <p>And for the better perfourmance hereof: be it enacted by aucthoritie aforesayd, that the Maiour of the Citie of London, and all othor Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iours, Baylifes, Shirifes, Constables, and other head officers of euery citie, and towne corporate, doe with al conuenient spede by themselfes, or theire sufficient deputies by them appoincted, before the feaste of the Purification next comming, and so from tyme to tyme, euery Moneth once, make a view and examination of aged, impotent, and lame {per}sōs, beggers, as be within the precincte of their iurisdiction, and see all such as were not borne, nor hath been for the moste parte conuersaunt and abyding there by the space for three yeares complete, conueyed on hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sebacke, carte, or chariotte, or otherwise, as shall seeme by theire discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to the next Constables, and they to conueigh the same to the next Cōstables, &amp; so from Constables to Constables, till the sayd persons be brought to the place where they were borne, or most conuersaunt and abiding, as is aforesayde, there to be prouided for, kepte, and nourished of almose, as is aforesayde: vpon the paine that euerye suche Mayour, Shirife, or Constable, head borough, or head officer not making viewe not sending or conueyghing awaye, not receiuing, or not prouiding, as is before appointed, according to the true purport or meaninge of thys acte, to forfeyte for euerye suche defaulte xl.s. Whereof the one halfe to the kynges vse, the other to the partie that will sue therefore in anye of the kynges courts of Recorde, by bill, information, action of debt, in the which suites, none essoine, wager of law, nor protectiō shalbe allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that yf any of the sayde aged, maymed, or impotēt persones of the Cities, townes, or villages where they were borne in, or had their most abiding, as is aforesayde, be not so lame or impotent, but that they may worke in some maner of worke: that then suche citie, Towne, Parishe, or Village, doe eyther in common prouide some suche worke for them, as they may bee occupied in, or appointe them to suche as will finde them woorke for meate and drinke. And yf theye refuse of wilfulnesse and stubburnesse to worke, or doe runne away, and begge in other places, then to punishe the same according to theire discretions,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150873:9"/> with cheyning, beating, or otherwise, as shal seeme to them conuenient. And for the more furtheraunce of the reliefe of suche whiche are in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained misery, and to whom charitie ought to be extended: be it enacted by aucthoritie aforesayde, that euery Sundaye and holy daye, after the reading of the Gospell of the day, the Curate of euery parishe do make, (according to suche talent as God hath geuen hym) a godlye and briefe exhortation to hys Parishioners: mouing and exciting them to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre the poore people, and the duetie of Christian charitie, in relieuing of them, whiche bee their brethren in Christe, borne in the same Parishe, &amp; neding their helpe.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that if it shal chaunce anye such adiudged appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, seruaunt, or slaue, as is before rehearsed, to haue inheritaunce des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cēded vnto him, or her, or any other wayes, by the lawes of thys realm̄, warde, or bondeman, or neife of bloude, by, or from anye of hys aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoures, to any persone or persones: That then it shalbe lawfull to anye suche persone or persones, to whome anye suche warde, bonde man, or neife shall apperteigne, to sease and take suche wardes, bonde men, or neifes, and them to reteigne and kepe, as theyre wardes, bonde men, or neifes, And the sayde wardes, bonde men, and neifes shalbe discharged of the said slauery, or other seruitude, or bondage aboue rehersed: Thys estatute, or any thing therein conteined, to the contrary in any wise not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
            <p>And also bee it enacted, that if anye suche seruaunt, apprentice, slaue, or slaues, whiche shall haue at any time hereafter any aduauncement or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, accrue, come, or growe vnto hym, or anye of them, whereby hee, or they may haue a conuenient liuing, that then, and from thenceforth, hee or they so being aduaunced, to be discharged of their slauery, seruitude, and bondage: thys Acte, or any thing therein conteined to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding. Any woman being a seruaūt, apprentice, or slaue, as is aforesaide, being maried within the age of xx. yeres, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the assent of her maister, vntill she shal accomplishe and come to the sayde age of xx. yeres, onely excepted.</p>
            <p>Bee it also enacted, that all Leprouse, and poore beddered creatures, whatsoeuer they bee, may at theyr owne libertie remayne and continue in such houses appointed for leprouse, or beddred people, as they now be in, &amp; shal not be compelled to repayre into any other coūtreys or places, by the vertue of thys acte: any thing therin cōteined to the cōtrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding. And that also it shalbe lefull vnto the sayd Leprouse and beddred people, for theire better reliefes, to appointe their Proctor or Proctors, so there be not appointed aboue the number of two persons, for anye one house of Leprouse beddred people, to gather the charitable almose of all such inhabitauntes, as shalbee within the compasse of .iiii. myles of any of the sayde houses of leprous and beddred persons.</p>
            <p>And be it ordeyned and enacted by the auctoritie abouesayde, that it
<pb facs="tcp:150873:10"/> shalbe lawful to euery persone, to whom anye persone in fourme aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, shalbe adiudged a slaue, to put a ring of yron about hys necke, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, or hys legge, for a more knowlege and suertie of the keping of hym. And that if any persone or persones do take, or helpe to take anye suche bonde of yron from anye suche slaue, that then euerye persone so doinge without the licence or assent of hys maister, shall forfayte for euery suche defaute x. poundes sterling.</p>
            <p>Be it further enacted, that thys present acte shall before the firste daye of Marche next comming, be openly proclaimed in euerye Citie, Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate towne, and market Towne, vpon the market daye: and also from thenceforth shall yerely bee read in euery Shyre openly in two general quarter sessions of the peace, that is to say, at the general quarter sessiōs after Midsomer, and the general quarter sessiōs next after Christemas, to the intent that euery persone may haue knowledge thereof, and that thys acte shall endure vnto the ende of the next Parlament.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; be it enacted, that it shalbe lawfull to the Lorde Chauncelour of England, or the Lord keper of the great Seale for the tyme being at theire discretions to graunt commission vnder the greate seale of Englande, to euery, or any persone or persones that hath, or shal haue hys or theire houses or barnes burnt, or suche losses, to gather the reliefe and charitie of others for theire ayde and helpe, of hys or theire losses, decay, or hinderaunce, as in time past hath been vsed: any thinge conteined in thys acte notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte for Tenures holden in <hi>Capite.</hi> ¶ The .iiii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here before this time, ambiguities, q̄stions, &amp; doubts haue been moued &amp; stirred in diuers &amp; sundry y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kings courtes of Recorde, whether suche honours, castles, manours, landes, tenem̄ts, &amp; other hereditam̄ts are holden of the kyng in <hi>Capite,</hi> whiche any hys louing subiectes doe holde by knightes seruice, Socage, or other seruices of the king, as of his Duchies, Erledo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, Baronies, honours, castles, manours, landes, tenements, fees, and seignouries, which haue come to the handes &amp; possessiō of diuers of his hyghenes most noble progenitours, by atteindour of treason, misprision of treason, atteindours of <hi>Premunire,</hi> &amp; prouision had &amp; doen by acte of Parlamēt, by verdicte, cōfession, conuictiō, or vtlagarie, &amp; offices or no offices thereupon founde, or by the dissolution, surrender, or geuing vp to the kyng, or to any hys noble Progenitours, of any religious or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical houses or places, or of anye Manoures, Landes, Tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and other hereditaments, to anye of the same religious or Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stycal houses or places in anye wise appertaininge or belonging, or no: By meanes of whiche doubte so moued, hys sayde humble and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Subiectes and tenauntes haue been heretofore muche vnquieted,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150873:10"/> molested, and greued: wherfore the kynge our souereigne Lorde, myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and entierlye desiring the quietnesse of hys sayde Subiectes, and that the certaintie of hys lawes in that behalfe myght bee knowen, and declared to hys sayde louing subiectes, for a plaine declaration and reso<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lution to bee had, of, for, and concerning the premysses at the humble pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition and suite of the Lordes and commons in thys present Parlamēt assembled, doth ordeyne, declare, and enacte by the assent of the Lordes Spiritual and temporal, and of the commons in this present Parlamēt assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that all suche Honoures, Castles, Manours, Landes, Tenementes, and other hereditamentes, and euerye of them, whiche nowe bee, or at anye tyme hereafter shalbe holden of the kyng, or of any of hys heires or successours, by anye of hys sayde Subiectes, by knyghtes seruice, Socage, or otherwise, as of any of his or their Dukedomes, Earledomes, Baronies, Castles, manours, Landes, Tenementes, Fees, or Seignories, whiche bee come to the Kynge, or hys moste noble progenitoures, or hereafter shall come to the Kyng, hys heyres or successours, by meanes of any suche Attainder, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiction, vtlagarie, or of any suche dissolution, surrendre, or geuing vp of anye Religious or Ecclesiastical houses or places, or of any Manours, landes, tenementes, or hereditamentes, to anye of the sayd religious or Ecclesiasticall houses or places in anye wise belonging or apperteining, shall not from henceforth bee adiudged, deemed, taken or construed to any intent, cōstruction or purpose, to be holden in <hi>Capite,</hi> or as Tenure in <hi>Capite:</hi> anye ambignitie, question, or doubte heretofore moued to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by the auctoritie aforesayd, that thys act or any thing therin conteyned, shall not in any wise be preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ne hurteful to the kynge, hys heires or successours, to, for, or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any wardeship, liuery, primer season, fine for alienation, or to, or for any other profite or aduauntage, whiche now is come, or hereafter shal, or maye come, fall, or growe to the kyng, hys heyres, or successoures, by or from any persone or persones, whiche now doth, or hereafter shal hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de any honours, seigniouries, castles, manours, landes, tenementes, or other hereditaments of the kyng in Chiefe, as of hys persone, or of any other hys auncient possessions, and being not come to the kyng by anye suche attainder, confession, conuiction, vtlagarie, dissolution, geuing vp, or surrender, as bee abouesayde.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that thys present act, or any thing therein conteined, or specified, shall not in anye wyse, or by anye meanes, geue anye aduauntage, libertie, or profit to anye Tenaunt or owner in Fee simple, of anye Honours, Manours, Landes, tenementes, or other hereditamentes, whiche haue heretofore sued anye special or general liuerie, or <hi>ouster le mayne,</hi> out of the handes of the kynge, or of anye hys noble Progenitours, of anye Honours,
<pb facs="tcp:150873:11"/> manours, landes, tenementes, or other hereditamentes, by what tenor or seruice they were, or be holden, or that haue, or shall confesse by anye mater of record, any tenor in chiefe of the king, but that they, their heirs and assignes shall haue and holde the same manours, landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and other hereditaments, in like maner and fourme, as they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the making of thys present Act, &amp; as though thys present Acte had neuer been had, ne made: any thing aboue declared and enacted to the contrarye notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte that no horses shalbe conueighed out of thys Realme, and other the kynges dominions without licence. ¶ The .vi. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here before thys tyme, diuers of the kynges Subiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and namely of the North partes of thys Realme, aswel in time of peace as of warre, haue conueighed, sold, geuē, &amp; deliuered out of thys realme, aswel into Stotland, as into other forein realmes, beyonde the Sea, many &amp; diuers greate multitude of horses, gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and mares, whiche haue been thought, aswell great occasion, strength &amp; boldnesse to the Scottishmen, &amp; other y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kings forein enemes, hauing in possession the same horses, geldings, &amp; mares, in time of warre to inuade this realm̄, as also a great decay of the good breede of horses and mares, whiche before tyme hath been within thys realme, to the great detriment &amp; hinderaūce of the kynges poore subiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes towardes the defence of thys realme and other hys deminions. For remedy wherof: be it therfore enacted by our souereigne lord the kyng, &amp; by the commons in thys present parlament assembled, &amp; by the aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the same, that yf anye persone or persones, after the firste daye of Ianuary next comming, doe sell, exchaūge, geue, conueigh, or deliuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the realme of Scotland, to the vse of any Scottisheman, or do carye, geue, exchaunge, sell, send, conueigh, or deliuer into anye place beyond y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sea out of thys realme, or the dominions of the same, any horse, gelding, or mare, without special licence therefore to bee obteined of the kynges highnes, or of hys heires, vnder the great seale of thys realme, or vnder the priuie signate: or if anye persone or persones, after the firste daye of Ianuary, do sell, exchaūge, geue, or deliuer to any Scottishman within this realme of England, or Wales, the townes of Berwike, or the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of the same, to thintent to be conueighed into Scotland, any horse, gelding, or mare, or do conueighe, or cary any horse, mare, or gelding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any forein parties beyond the sea, without like special licēce obteined of the kynges hyghnesse, or of hys heires, vnder the great seale, or priuie signate as is aforesayde: that then the same person and persons so offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding contrary to thys acte, shal lose and forfeyte to our souereigne lorde and hys heyres, the same horse, mare, or geldyng, so caried and conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed, and shall also lose and forfayte the summe of fourtie poundes for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150873:11"/> euery such horse, geldyng, or mare, so to be cōueighed &amp; caried in forme aforesaid: whereof the one moitie to bee to the kyng, &amp; the other moitie to hym, or thē, that will sue for the same, by information, action of debte, or detinue in any of the kynges courtes of Recorde, in whiche suite, no wager of lawe, essoine, ne protection shalbe allowed. And that also all &amp; euery persone and persones so offending, contrary to thys act, shal suffre imprisonement by the space of one whole yere.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that it shalbe leful, aswell to the warden &amp; wardens of the East, west, &amp; middle mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for the time being, in their warden courtes, as also to all and euery the kynges Iustices of Peace in euery shyre, aswell in Englande, as in Wales, in theire quarter sessions, to enquire of all and euerye offence or offences hereafter to be perpetrated, committed, or doen cōtrary to this act: And that it shalbe lefull to all and euery persone &amp; persons being the kynges subiectes, to arrest &amp; vnprison euery Scottishman, &amp; all &amp; euery other persone, or persones, whiche shall leade, or conueyghe contrarye to the meaning of thys Acte, any suche horse, geldyng, or mare, out of thys realme into the said realme of Scotland, or into any other foreine place beyond the sea, other then such persons, as hereafter shall haue sufficient warraunt, by, or from the kynges hyghnesse or hys heires, vnder hys, or their great seale, or priuie signate, according to the meaning of thys act.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that yf the kyng our soueraigne Lord, hys heires or successours, at any tyme hereafter, vnder his great seale, or priuie signate, doe geue licence to any persone or persones, to cary or conueigh any horses, mares, or geldings, into Stotland, or into any other parte beyond the Sea, or els doe geue aucthoritie, power, or commaundement to anye persone or persones, by warraunt, vnder the kynges great Seale, to licence any other person or persones to carye, or conueighe anye Horses, Mares, or geldynges into Scotlande, or into any parties beyond the sea, that then it shalbe lefull, aswell to all and singular person &amp; persons hauing suche licence vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kyngs great seale, or priuie signate, as to all and euery other person, and persons, hauing licence in writtinge vnder the seale of suche persone, or persones, to whom the kynge shall geue auctoritie, power, or commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in fourme abouesaid, to licēce other person or persons to cary or conueigh any horses, mares, or geldynges into Scotlande, or into anye parties beyond the sea, to cary &amp; cōueigh such nūbre of horses, geldings or mares, or any of them into Scotlād, or into any of the parties beyōd the sea, as shalbe mētioned in any such licence, as is before specified anye thing mētioned in thys act, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōtrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by the auctoritie aforesayd, that thys act, ne any thing therein conteined, shal in any wise extende, to any persone or persones, which at any time hereafter shall cary or conueighe any horse, Mare, or gelding into Scotlande, or into anye other foreine
<pb facs="tcp:150873:12"/> parties beyonde the sea, to serue the kyng in hys warres, with the same horses, Mares, or geldinges, anye thinge mencioned in thys acte, to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And to the intent the kynges Maiestie shal not hereafter be deceiued in the numbre of suche horses, mares, or geldinges, which hereafter shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be caried and conueighed into Scotlande, ne that the parties, whiche hereafter shal obtaine any licence by force of thys act, for the cariage or conueighaunce of any horses, mares, or geldynges, to bee caried or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyghed into Scotlande: Bee it therfore enacted by aucthoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide, that all and euery such persone &amp; persones, which hereafter shalbe licenced according to thys acte, to carie or conueigh any horses, mares, or geldynges into Scotlande, shall before the same cariage, or conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghaunce, vpon the peyne of forfeyture of the said horse, mare, or gelding or the double value thereof: whereof the one moitie to be to the kyng, &amp; the other moitie to him, or them that will sue for the same by suche like action, as before is limitted in thys acte, shewe hys or their said licence, to one of the three wardens of the three marches of Englande, to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that one of the said wardens shal cause the number of the said hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, mares, or geldynges so lycenced to bee conueighed into Scotlande, not onely to be kalēdard in a booke, to remaine in hys own custody: but also to be endorced and written on the backeside of the saide licence, and the same endorsement to be signed with the hande of the sayde warden.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that it shalbe lefull to euerye of the kynges Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, that shall passe ouer beyond the sea, to shyp and carye with them, horses, or geldynges, for theyr owne occupation in their iourneyes, and not to the intent to sell the same beyond the sea: And that intente to bee iudged by the othe of hym, or them, that so will cary ouer anye horse, or gelding, whiche othe shalbe taken before the Customers, or their depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or searcher of euery such Porte, where the same horse, or geldinge shalbe shipped before the shipping thereof.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that the warden of the fiue portes now being, or hereafter to be, may yerely at his pleasure, geue six horses, or geldings, &amp; no more, within one yere, at one, or diuers tymes, vpon like peine as is aforesaid, to any persone or persones, in the parties beyonde the seas, being in amitie with the kynges highnesse, or his successours: thys acte or any thing therein, to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that this acte, nor any thing therein mencioned, bee in any wise hurtful or preiudicial to the maister of the kynges horses, now &amp; hereafter to be, for such thinges &amp; cōmodities, as shall &amp; doe concerne his office, any thing in thys acte to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that it shalbe lefull to anye the kynges Subiectes, to cary, or sende into any partes beyond the sea, anye mares, whereof the price of any one mare so to be caried, doth not exceade .x.s. in suche and lyke maner, as Mares beynge of the price of vi.s. viii.d. haue beene, or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150873:12"/> might haue been conueighed ouer the Seas, before the makyng of this acte: any thing in thys act, or in any other act or actes heretofore made to the contrary hereof notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte for the continuaunce of makyng of wolsted yarne in Norffolke. ¶ The .vi. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the greatest, &amp; almost the whole numbre of the poore inhabitaunts of the countie of Norffolke, &amp; the citie of Norwiche, be, and haue been heretofore for a great time mainteined, &amp; gotten theire liuing by spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the wolles growing in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said countie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke vpon the rock into yarne, &amp; by all the saide time haue vsed to haue their accesse to common markettes within the said coūtie and citie, to buye theire wolles there to be spūne as is aforesaide, of certaine persones called retailers of the same wolles be eight peny worth, and twelue peniworth at one tyme or thereabout, and haue not vsed to buye, ne can buye theire saide wolle of the breders of the same wolles by such small parcelles, aswell for that the sayde bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the sayde wolles will not sell their said wolles by such small par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles, as also for that the most parte of the sayde poore persones dwell farre of from the said breders of the said wolles: And forasmuche as by an acte of Parlament made in the xxxvii. yere of the reigne of the noble king of famous memorie Henry the viii. all persones be restreigned vpō a great paine, to bye any wolles to sell y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same againe, except merchaūts of the Staple, for the onely prouision of the Staple, as in the sayd acte emong other thinges more at large it is conteined: therfore the said re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailers of wolles in the said countie of Norfolke and citie of Norwiche, whiche heretofore haue vsed to buye wolles, and to sell them agayn to the saide poore persones in ouert markettes as is aforesayd, haue synce the makyng of the said estatut in eschewing the daunger and peyne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided by the same, ceassed and left to bye the sayd wolles, for the reliefe of the sayde poore persones: By reason wherof, the same poore persones inhabiting within the saide countie of Norffolke and citie of Norwich, that hath heretofore been spinners, and mainteined by spinninge of the sayde wolles, be now vnoccupied and vnset a worke, and a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of them inforced to begge for lacke of worke, to the vtter decay and ruyne of the poore people of the said Countie and Citie, and the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes thereof, vnlesse some remedy be therin prouided. In considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion whereof, it may please the kyngs most royal maiestie, by the assent of the lordes spiritual &amp; temporal, &amp; the commons in thys present parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment assembled, and by auctoritie of the same, that all and euery person and persones dwelling and inhabiting within the saide countie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke and citie of Norwiche, or in eyther of them, by his, or thē selfes, or
<pb facs="tcp:150873:13"/> by his, or their factours, seruaunt or seruauntes may lawfully frō hens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth without peine, forfaiture, daungier, or breache of anye lawe or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce, to buie and bargain wolles, and take and make prouision to buie or bargain wolles growing, or that shal grow only within the said coūtie of Norfolke, in as large and like maner and fourme as the same inhabitauntes within the sayde coūtie and Citie might, &amp; did vse to do before the making of the saide acte of Parlament, &amp; as the sayde acte of Parlament had neuer been had or made, so that the same person and {per}<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons so buiynge or barganing, or makinge promise to buye or bargaine the saied wolles, do sell or retaile the same againe in the common mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, or other open place within the saide countie of Norfolke, or Citie of Norwiche, to any persone or persones at their pleasure and libertie that will bie the same, or any parcel therof, dwelling and inhabiting within the saide countie and citie of Norwiche, or any of them, that shall or will spinne the same within the saide countie of Norfolke, and Citie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiche, or any of them: the sayd former acte, or any article, clause or sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence therein contained, or any other acte or actes, lawe, or ordinaunce heretofore made, to the contrarie thereof in anye wise notwithstāding.</p>
            <p>And where in the Parlamēt holden at westminster the xxxiii. yere of the reigne of our saide late Souereine Lord the Kyng, it was amongst other thinges enacted thus, as ensueth, or like in effect, that is to saye, that no persone or persones from hensefoorth, shoulde buye, ne cause to bee boughte within the sayde Citye of Norwiche, or Countie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke, anye yarne spunne of the rocke, called wolsted yarne, the whiche shoulde then after that bee spunne within the sayde Countye or Citie, but suche person or persons beinge weuers of woolsted, Russels, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Saies, and suche other like Clothes, within the saide Citye or Countie, that shoulde weue or worke, or cause to be wouen or wrought in woolsted, Stamine, Russelles, Saies, or suche other like clothes, the sayde yarne so bought, or caused to bee bought within the sayde Citye or Countie, in the Citie of Norwiche, or in some market towne within the sayde Countie: vpon the peine and forfeiture for euerye pounde weight of the said yarne called wolsted yarne, so bought within the said Countie or Citie, and not wouen or wrought, as is aforesayde, within the sayde Citie or countie, fourtie shillinges, the one halfe therof to be to the king our souereigne Lord, and the other halfe thereof to be to hym, or them that shoulde then after that sue for the same by byll, informaciō, action of dette, or otherwise in anye courte of Recorde, in whiche sayde action, bill, or information, no essoine, wager of law, foreine plee, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection shoulde bee allowed. And where it is also ordeined in the sayde acte, that yf anye persone or persones, did after the first day of April thē next after the said acte ensuing, ship, or carie, or conueigh, or cause to bee shipped, to carie, or conueigh into the parties beyond the Sea, or did ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or conueigh into the partes beyond the sea, any yarne called woolsted
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:150873:13"/> yarn not made, or wrought in cloth, so that such yarn were spūne with in thys Realme, that then euery person &amp; persones so shipping, cōueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and carying, or causing such yarne so to be shipped, caried, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighed should forfayt for euery pounde of woolsted yarne so shypped, conueighed, or caried .xl.s. the one halfe thereof to be to our saide So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lorde the kyng, &amp; the other halfe therof to him, or them that should sue for the same, by bill, informacion, or accion of debte in any of the kyngs courts of Record, as in the said acte the same, or the lyke in effect, more plainely dooth &amp; may appeare. And forasmuche as the sayd acte was made &amp; ordeined to continue &amp; endure vntil the Parliament then after that next ensuing, &amp; hath been sithens by other general actes continued vntill this present Parliament, &amp; was not by any of the said actes ordeined to continue for euer: It may now please the kings most excellent maiesty, with thassent of the Lordes Spirituall &amp; temporall, &amp; the commons in this present Parliament assembled, &amp; by aucthoritye of the same, that all the afore resited acte for yarne, with al the words, forfaitures, paines, &amp; sentences before recited, as the same before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and declared, may from henceforth be enacted to continue, &amp; to bee taken for an acte to cōtinue for euer to al intents &amp; purposes, according to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said words, sētences, &amp; the purport therof before in this act recited</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies that it shalbe leful to euery person &amp; persones, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a hatte maker, or hat makers, dwelling within y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said citye of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiche, to buy such of the sayd woolsted yarne, as is called and knowen by the name of middle vffe yarne, as they and euery of them haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore done, &amp; vsed to doe, so that the same middle vffe yarne so bought by the said hatmakers, or hatmaker, be wrought in hattes, or emploied to hatmaking within the saide citie, any thing before recited, to the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereof notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .vii. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte for the continuance of Actions after the death of any king.</head>
            <p>WHere the Kynges subiectes heretofore haue to theire greate costes, charges, and expences, prosecuted, and sued dyuerse and sundrye Actions, aswell reall and personall, as all other Actions mixte, or otherwyse, in the kynges Maiestyes courts and other courtes of recorde, not onelye by wryttes, but also by plaint or bylles, whiche actions, suites, bylles, and plaintes, by the deathe, or demyse of the Kynges of this Realme, haue been dyscontinued, and the parties in euery suche accions, suites, billes, &amp; playntes, therby haue been put without day, wherby the demaundaunts, playntifes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours in euery suche action and suite were compelled and driuen by the order of the lawes of this realme, for their further remedy, to cōmence &amp; begin again his, or their saide actions, suites, or plaints, or els to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute, &amp; sue resommons, attachements, <hi>Scire facias,</hi> or suche other like,
<pb facs="tcp:150873:14"/> processe to reuiue his or their said actions, sutes, or plaints, which was not onelye to their great costes, charges, expences, hinderaunces, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of theire causes &amp; suites, but also a greate lette and hynderaunce of iustice, for reformacion wherof, be it ordeined, established, &amp; enacted by the king our souereigne Lorde, &amp; the Lordes &amp; commons in thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent parliament assembled, and by the aucthorytye of the same, that frō henceforth by the death, or demise of the kings Maiestie that now is, (whose life almightie God long preserue, kepe &amp; maintain in his moste royal estate) nor by the death or demise of any y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hereafter shalbe kinge of this Realme, any accion, suite, bill, or plaint, nowe, or that hereafter shall depende betwene party and party in any of the courtes aforesaid shal not in any wise be discontynued, or put without day: But that the processe, plees, demurres, and continuaunces in euerye action, actyons, suites, bylles, or plaintes, whiche nowe, or that hereafter shal depende shall stand good and effectual, and be prosecuted, &amp; sued forthe in suche maner &amp; fourme, &amp; in the same estate, cōdicion and order, as if the same king had liued, or continued in full life, the deathe or demise hereafter of any king of this Realme notwithstandyng. And that all &amp; all maner of iudicial processe that hereafter shalbe had, or pursued in the time of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reigne of any other king, then reigned at the time of the pursuite of the original, or other former processe, shalbe made in the name of the kyng, that for the time shall reigne, and be king of this realme, and that vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce touching the same processe betwene the names of the kings, shal not be in any wise material, as concerning any defaulte to bee alleged, or obiected therefore.</p>
            <p>And also be it further established and enacted by thaucthority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al &amp; euery <hi>Assise of nouel disseisin, assise of mortdauncestour, Iuris vtrum,</hi> &amp; atteint, which at any time hereafter shalbe arreygned, cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced or sued before any of the kings Iustices of assise, shal not from hēce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be discontinued or put without day, by reason of death, new com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, associacion, or not cōming of the same Iustices of assise, or anye of them, but shal stand good &amp; effectual in the lawe, to all intents, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions and purposes, the death, new commission associacion, or not cōming of the same Iustices, or any of thē, in any wise notwithstāding.</p>
            <p>And ouer that, be it ordeined &amp; enacted by the aucthority aforesaide, that albeit any demaundaunt or plaintife in any maner of accion, byll, or suite, shall fortune to bee made, or created Duke, Archebishop, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, Earle, Viscount, Baron, Bishop, Knight, Iustice of the one bēch, or of the other, or Sergeaunt at lawe, depending the same accion, bill, or suite, yet that notwithstanding, that no writ, action, or suite, shall for such cause in anye wise bee abatable or abated, but shal remaine in like force, goodnes, &amp; strength, as the same was before, anye lawe, or vsage to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And also be it ordeined and enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:150873:14"/> albeit any person, or persons beyng Iustice of assyse, Iustyce of Gaole delyuery: or Iustice of peace within any of the kings dominions, or be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing in any other of the kings commissions whatsoeuer, shall fortune to be made, or created Duke, Archebishop, Marques, Earle, Viscoūt, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Bishop, Knight, Iustyce of thone benche, or of the other, or sergeāt at law, or sheryf, yet that notwithstāding, he, &amp; they shal remain iustyce &amp; cōmissioner, &amp; haue ful power &amp; auctoritie to execute the same, in like maner &amp; forme, as he, or they might, or ought to haue dō before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same.</p>
            <p>And be it ordeined &amp; enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that in al cases, where any persone, or persones heretofore haue ben, or hereafter shalbe found gilty of any maner of treason, murder, manslaughter, rape or other felony whatsoeuer, for the which iudgement of death should, or may ēsue, &amp; shalbe repried to prison without iudgement at that time geuen agaynst him, her, or them so found gilty, that those persons that at any time hereafter shal by the kinges letters Patentes bee assigned Iustices to deliuer the Gaole, where any such person or persons found giltie shall remaine, shal haue ful power and aucthoritie to geue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of death against such person so founde gilty, and repried, as the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same iustices (before whom suche person or persons was, or were foūd gilty) might haue done, if their cōmission of Gaole deliuery had remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; contynued in full force &amp; strength. And ouer that, that no maner of processe, or suit made, sued, or had before any Iustyces of Assise, gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le delyuery, <hi>Oyer and terminer,</hi> iustice of peace, or other of the Kynges cōmissyoners, shal, ne in any wise be discontinued by the making &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of any new commission or associaciō, or bee altering of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> names of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iustices of assise, gaole deliuery, <hi>Oyer and terminer,</hi> iustices of peace or other the kings commissioners, but that the newe iustices of assise, Gaole deliuery, and of the peace, &amp; other cōmissioners maye procede in euerye behalfe, as if the olde commissions, and Iustices, &amp; commyssyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners had styll remained &amp; continued not altered.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The viii. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte for the confirmacion of letters Patentes.</head>
            <p>WHere the Kinges most excellent highnesse sithen the .xxviii. day of Ianuarie, in the firste yeare of hys Maiestyes reygne, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well vpon dyuerse and sundry good consideracions, hys Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestye specyallye mouyng, as also otherwyse, hathe bargay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, solde, exchaunged, geuen, restored, and graunted by hys graces seuerall letters Patentes, indentures, or other wrytynges sealed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hys hyghnesse greate Seale of Englande, the Seale of hys Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of Lancaster, and the seale of the Courte of Augmentacion, &amp; the Reuenues of his crowne, or any of them, as wel to bodies politique &amp; corporate, as to diuers and sundry of his louing and obediēt subiects, diuerse and sundrye honours, castelles, maners, landes, tenementes, rentes, reuercions, seruices, personages appropriated, aduowsons,
<pb facs="tcp:150873:15"/> tithes, oblacyons, pencions, porcyons, fraunchises, priuileges, liberties &amp; other hereditaments, commodityes &amp; profites in fee simple, fee tayle, for terme of life, or lyues, or for terme of yeares, as in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same seueral let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patents, Indentures, &amp; other writings is mencyoned &amp; declared: In auoiding, disturbing, hurting, or hindering of the saide seuerall let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes, Indentures, and other writinges, and of the saide man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, landes, tenementes, hereditamentes, and other thynges in them conteined, sundry and manye ambiguities, doubtes, &amp; questions haue or myght hereafter happē to be moued, obiected, alleged, inuented, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, or sterred, aswel for misnaming, misrecital, or none recital of any of the same Honours, castelles, manours, landes, tenements, and other the premisses, or any parcell therof, or for lacke of fyndyng of offyces, or inquisicions, of, and in the premisses, whereby the tytle of the Kynges highnes therin ought to haue been found before the makyng of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same letters patentes, or other writynge, or for misrecitall, or none recital of lesses therof before made, aswel of recorde as not of recorde, or for lack of the certeintye, miscasting, rating, or setting forth of the yerely values and rates of the premisses, or of the yerely rents reserued, of, and for the premisses, or any parcell therof mencioned, or conteyned in any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said letters patentes, or other writings, or for that the premysses bee, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part thereof is valued to a more, or lesse value in the said letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, or wrytings, then the saide honours, manours, lands, tenemēts and other the premisses then were or shalbe in yerely value, or for mys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naming of the townes, hamlettes, parishes, or counties, where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same honours, castelles, manbrs, landes, tenementes, rentes, hereditaments and other the premisses, and euery parcel therof, or anye parcell thereof lien, or beene, or for lacke of the true naminge of the natures, kyndes, sortes, and quantities of the saide possessions, or hereditamentes, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye parcel thereof, or for lacke of the true naming of the corporacion of the same bodies politique, or corporate, or for lacke of attornement, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, or season, or for misnaming of any of the late tenants, or fermors of the same premisses so solde, geuen, graunted, or exchaūged, as for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse and sundrie other suggestions and surmises, not comprised in the said letters patentes, which hereafter might happen to be moued, sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, or procured against the same letters patents. For remedye &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formacion wherof be it ordeined and enacted by the kinges most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent highnesse, with thassent of the Lordes Spirituall &amp; temporal, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōmons in this present parliament assembled, &amp; by thaucthoritye of the same, that aswel al &amp; euery the saide letters patēts, indentures, &amp; other wrytings, &amp; euery of thē sealed with, or vnder the seale or seales aboue named, or any of them made, or graunted by the kings highnes sithens the .xxviii. day of Ianuary last past, as also al and synguler hys graces letters patents, indentures, and other writings hereafter, during hys highnesse life (which our Lord long continue) to be had, made, or graū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:150873:15"/> with, or vnder any of the seales abouesaid, to any body politique, or corporate, or to any other person, or persones of any Honours, castelles manours, landes, tenementes, rents, reuercions, seruices, personages, tithes, pencions, porcions, aduowsons, nominaciōs, presentaciōs, fraū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chises, liberties, and other hereditamentes, commodities, possessions, &amp; profeictes, of what kinde, nature, or qualitye soeuer they, or any of thē be, is, or shalbe, or by whatsoeuer name or names they or any of them, be, is, or shalbe named, knowen, or reputed, shall stand &amp; bee taken, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted &amp; iudged good, sure, perfeict, effectual, &amp; auailable in the law, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> statutes in them limitted &amp; specified, to al intents, respectes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions &amp; purposes against the king his heires, &amp; successors without any confirmacion, lycence, dispensacion, or toleracion of the kynge, hys heires or successours: any the causes or matters aboue mencioned, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, or hereafter during his said highnes life to be conteined, had, or made in any such letters Patentes, indentures, or other writyngs by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kyng our Soueraigne lord, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> contrary in any wise notwithstandīg.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this act, ne any thing therin cōteined, shal not in any wise extende to reuiue, or make good any letters patents made of any office, or offices to any comptroller, customer, alneger, or sercher ne to any letters patentes of the graunte of any other office, or offyces heretofore graunted, or made by our saide Soueraigne lorde the king which now is, or be, or at any time heretofore haue bene adnichelated, determined, or made voide by iugement, by aucthoritie of parlyament or decree, nor to any patēt to be made to any person or persōs for terme of yeres, or during the minoritie of an heire, of, or in any manours, lāds or tenements, wherof any trauerse hereafter shalbe tēdred within thre monethes after any office founde and certified into anye of the kynges courtes of record, ne to any leasses, or grauntes of any manors, lands, or tenementes of our saide Soueraigne Lordes hereafter to bee made vnder anye of the Seales of the courts aforesayde, cōtrary to the limy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon, ordinaunce, prouision, establishment and aucthority of the same courts, any thyng in this act conteined to the contrary notw<seg rend="sup">t</seg>standing.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted, that this act, nor any thing therein conteined shal not extende to make any letters patentes of any offyce, or offyces, to be of any other effect, force, or strēgth, thē the same letters patents were, or should haue bene before the making of this act.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that al and singuler suche patentes, grauntees, donees, as any time hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter during the life of our said soueraigne Lord (whiche almighty God long preserue) shal fortune to haue, or obteine any Castelles, manours, landes, tenementes, tithes pencions, porcions, or other hereditaments of the gifte, graunt, sale, or exchange of the kynges Maiestye, or of the onely gifte of the kinges Maiestie, of his most lyberal dysposycion, and not solde, whiche at the day of the date of the letters Patents therof
<pb facs="tcp:150873:16"/> made, shalbe of more, or better yerely value to the king in yerelye rente and ferme, then shalbe conteined, mencioned, and specified in any suche letters patentes, and particulers thereof made by the particuler Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyour, or Surueiours thereof, &amp; in such byll or billes, as shalbe signed and sealed with the hand, or hands of the patentee, or patentees therof to be exhibyted to the kings Maiestye, or his officer or offycers, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in whose suruey the said manours, landes, and tenementes, and other the premisses, or any parte therof shalbe, or within any of them, whiche bill shalbe signed, sealed, had, and made, as is aforesaide, before any bil shalbe therof signed by the kyngs Maiestie, that then euery of the said patentees, grauntees, and donees, their heires, executours, and admy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistratours within one yeare next after due proufe, and decrees therof made and had in the courte, within whose surueye the same castelles, manours, landes, tenementes, &amp; other the premisses, or any parcel ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, before the said gifts and grauntes were, shal content and pay to the king for the same ouerplus, &amp; more value of the same manours, lands, tenementes, tithes, pencions, portions, &amp; other hereditamentes to hym solde, or exchaunged, after such rate, as other landes, and tenementes were before to him sold or exchaunged, and for the ouerplus and more value of suche landes and tenementes as shal happen to be geuen by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kings Maiesty, and not solde, as is abouesaid, the saide patentee, hys heirs, executours, or administratours shal content and pay to the king after the rate of twenty yeres purchase, so that the same proufe and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cree be had, &amp; made in maner &amp; fourme abouesaid, within .x. yeres next after the date of the saide letters patentes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .ix. Chapiter. ¶ An Acte for the vniting of certein churches within the city of Yorke.</head>
            <p>WHere in the auncyent citie of Yorke and suburbes of the same there are manye parishe churches, whiche heretofore the same beyng well inhabited and replenished with people, were good and honest liuinges for learned Incumbents, by reason of the pryuie tythes of the ryche marchauntes, and of the offrings of a great multitude, whyche liuinges is nowe so muche decaied by the ruin and decaye of the saide citye, and of the trade of marchaundyse there, that the reuenues and profites of diuers of the same benefyces are at thys present not aboue the clere yerely value of .xxvi.s̄. viii.d. so that a great sort of them are not a compentent and honest liuing for a good curate: yea, and no persone will take the cure, but that of necessitye there is some chaunterie Priest, or elles some late Relygious persone beyng a stypendarie taken and appointed to the saide cure and benefyce, which for the moste parte are vnlearned, and verye ignoraunt personnes, not able to doe anye parte of their duties: By reason whereof the saide ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is not onely replenished with blinde guides and Pastours, but also
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:150873:16"/> the people muche kept in ignoraunce, aswell of their duties towardes God, as also towardes the kinges Maiestie, and the common wealthe of this realme, and to the great daunger of their soules: In considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciō wherof, and for the better relief and order of the saide citie, it maye please the kinges maiesty by thassent of the lordes spirituall &amp; tēporall and the commons in this present parliament assēbled, &amp; by thaucthory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the same, that from henceforth it shalbe lawfull to the Maior, &amp; Recorder of the saide citie, &amp; the ordinary or his deputie, &amp; vi. Iustices of peace in the said citie, to vnyte &amp; knit together the said parishes into fewer number, that is to wete, so many of the said parishes into one pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rish, as to them shalbe thought conuenient to be a liuing for one honest incumbent, so the cleare yerely value of one parishe excede not .xx. li. by yere, and so to procede through the saide citie and suburbs of the same. And that it shalbe lefull for the saide Maior, Recorder, and Aldermen, to pull downe the churches, whiche they shal think superfluous in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said citie and suburbes of the same, and to bestowe the same toward y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reparacions and enlargement of other churches, of the bridges in the saide citie, and to the relyefe of the poore people, And further, that the said Maior, Recorder, Ordinarie, or his deputy, &amp; .vi. Iustices of peace being Aldermen, shal allot &amp; appoint the presentment &amp; patronage of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church so vnited to the patrons of al the churches, to knit in one parish that they may make their presentments by turne, euery one according to their quantitie of his former patronage.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> al such incumbents of the churches aforesayde, that shalbe put downe by vertue of this act, shall haue the yerely value of their benefices after the rate they do pay tenthes during their liues, so they wyll do seruyce therfore in the churches appointed for the parish churche, according to their former duties: And if they refuse to serue, then they onely during their liues to haue the thirde parte of the value as is aforesaid, &amp; to be paied at the hands of the incumbent of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parish church to be appointed</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by thaucthority aforesayd, that the incumbents of euery such church, which by vertue of this acte shallbe made and ordeyned for the parish churche, &amp; whereunto any other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishe, or parishes shalbe vnited, shal after the vnion therof, yerelye pay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the tenthes to be due for the same to the kynges Maiestie, his heires &amp; successours of the same churche, and of al other churches therunto vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; annexed. And the sayd incumbents of the parishe churche so vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to haue his allowance of the incumbents of the churches so vnited therunto, during their seueral liues, according to the rate and porciō of the churches so vnited, as shalbe assigned by the abouesaid persons, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing aucthoritie by this acte to vnite the same. And the successor &amp; suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours of euery such incumbēt of euery such churche, as shall be made the parishe churche, &amp; wherunto any churche or parishe shall bee vnited
<pb facs="tcp:150873:17"/> by force of thys act, shall pay, or compounde for the first fruites thereof at euery auoidaunce before his induction to the same, according to such yerely value, at such church or churches, as shalbe made a parish church &amp; whereunto any church, or churches, parish, or Parishes shalbe vnited by force of this act, shalbe of, at the time of the vnion therof, and as if it had been of suche like yerely value at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time of making of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> statute for first fruites and tenthes, and of no greater value: any ordinaunce, sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, or lawe, to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .x. Chapiter. ¶ An acte for exigentes &amp; Proclamacions in Wales, &amp; in the Countye Palantine of Chester, &amp; also in the citie of Chester.</head>
            <p>WHere in the high Court of Parliament holden at westmynster the .xxvii. yere of the most prosperous reigne of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> late famous king Henry the eight, by the assent of the Lordes Spirytuall and Temporall, and the commons assembled in the saide high Courte of Parliament: it was enacted and establyshed by aucthoritye of the same Parlyamente, that hys highnesse dominion and princypalytie of Wales, and of manours, landes, tenementes, and other domynyons wythin the sayde domynion and pryncipalitye of Wales should be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded into twelue Shyeres, or Counties, that is to saye, the Shieres or counties of Glamorgan, Radnour, Brecknok, Karmerthen, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke, Cardigan, Merionneth, Mongomerie, Flinte, Carnaruan, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glesie, &amp; Denbigh, in euery of whiche saide counties &amp; shyeres, emongst the officers yerely appointed, it was thē ordayned that there should be distinct and seueral shirifes yearelye, &amp; also where the counties Palan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of Chester, and of the citie of Chester, be auncient and seueral coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Palantine of thēselues, in al which said counties, the kyngs wryt hath not, nor yet doth not runne: So that the proclamacion awarded vpon any exigent against any persone or persons, in any accion, wherin processe of outlawry dothe lye according to the statute made in the .vi. yere of the reigne of the saide late king, cānot be directed vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shirife or shirifes of any of the saide shires or counties, but vnto the shirife of the countye next adioyning: So that the party dwellyng in any of the said shieres or counties, agaynst whom anye suche exigent and procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion shalbe so awarded, shall not, nor cā haue any knowledge of the same sure, or processe, by reason wherof many of the persōs inhabitinge in the saide shieres and counties, without knowledge, or cause of suite, haue ben wrōgfully and vniustly vtlaged to their vtter vndoing.</p>
            <p>Be it therfore, &amp; for diuerse other good consideracions, by the king our souereigne Lord, with the assent of the Lordes Spirituall &amp; tēporall, and the commons in this present Parliamente assembled, &amp; by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the same enacted, ordeyned, and establyshed, that if and whē soeuer any writ of exigent at any time after the first daye of April next comming shalbe awarded at the suite of the king, or of any other persō
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:150873:17"/> or persones plaintife, or plaintifes, in any accion or suite, in anye of the courtes of our saide Soueraigne lord the king, his heires or successors commonly called the kinges benche, and the common place, againste a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny person, or persons, dwelling in any of the aforesaide counties in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, or in the said counties Palantine of Chester, or the city of Chester, or in any of them: that then immediatly vpon the awarding of euerye such exigent, the Iustice or Iustices before whom any such wryt of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igent vpon such suite, or action shalbe sued, shal haue full &amp; aucthoritye to awarde one writ of proclamacion according to the tenour &amp; effect of Proclamacions awarded vpon exigentes, directed out of any of the saide courtes in London, against any persone dwellinge in anye other shiere, where the kynges writ is curraunt, according to the order and fourme of the sayde statute made in the .vi. yere of the said late king to be directed to such of the aforesaid shirifes of any of the aforesayd coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in wales, &amp; of the counties Palantine of Chester, and of the city of Chester for the time being, where it shall happen the said defendant, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom any such action shalbe sued, as is aforesaid, to be dwellīg And that euery such writ of Proclamation shal haue the same <hi>teste</hi> and day of returne, as thexigents, wherupon euery such writ of Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion shalbe awarded, shal haue: And that euery suche shiryfe to whom any such writ of Proclamaciō shalbe directed, shal make Proclamacyō of the said writ of proclamacion, according to the tenour of the same, &amp; &amp; shal make true returne of the same in such court, &amp; before such iustices as the tenour of the same writ shal require &amp; demaund. And y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al outla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries hereafter to be promulged, or pronounced against anye persone or persons vpon any such exigent, or exigents, awarded against any persō or persons, dwelling in any of the said counties of wales, &amp; the coūties Palantine of Chester, &amp; of the citie of Chester, &amp; no writ of Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion awarded in fourme abousaid, to the shyrife, or shirifes of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, where the party defendaūt shalbe, as is abouesaid, dwelling, or not returned, to be clerely voide, and of none effecte, nor force in the lawe.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthority aforesaid, that al &amp; euery shierife and shierifes of euery of the said counties of Wales, and of the counties Palantine of Chester, and of the cytye of Chester aforesayde shall haue in euery of the saide courtes of the kynges Benche, &amp; of the common place, one sufficient Deputie at the least, to receiue all wrytts directed to suche the shiryfe, or shierifes, for whom the same Deputie or deputies shalbe appointed, in like maner, and fourme, and vpon like peines, as by the former statutes &amp; lawes of this realme other shirifes of other shires, or counties within this realme of Englande be boūden to haue, in either of the same courtes: and that all writtes of proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion aforesaide shalbe deliuered vnto euery suche Deputy of Recorde in the same courtes, and also like fees shalbee payde for making euerye suche writ of proclamacion, and for enrolling the same of Recorde, as is
<pb facs="tcp:150873:18"/> limitted in the said statute made in the said sixt yere of the reigne of our said late Souereigne lord king Henry the eight.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthority aforesaid, that if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son dwellyng in any of the saide counties of Wales, after the aforesaid first day of April, shalbe outlawed in any suite, or action aforesaid, that then writs of special <hi>Capias vtlagaf;</hi> single <hi>Capias vtlagat{ur}, nō molestand'</hi> and all other processe, for, or against any persone outlawed, shal, &amp; may frō thenceforth be directed to the sherief of any of the saide counties in Wales, as immediate officers to the kings said courtes of the kynges benche, or common place in that behalfe: and that euery suche writtes may be deliuered of recorde to the deputie of suche of the saide sherifes, to whom any suche writ, or processe shalbe directed, &amp; that euerye suche shirife shal make execucion and returne of euery suche writte of processe to him directed, vpon like peyne &amp; penaltie, as is aboue limytted.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted &amp; established, that if any such writ, or writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Proclamacion hereafter directed to any of the shirifes of anye of the saide shieres in Wales, or counties Palantyne of Chester, or of the citie of Chester, be deliuered vnto any of the saide sherifes for the tyme being, or to his or their deputy, in maner &amp; forme aforesaid: &amp; the same sherife or sherifes do not make true returne of euery suche writ &amp; writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Proclamacion, into such courte &amp; courtes, out of which the saide writ, or writtes of Proclamacion shalbe awarded: that for euery such faulte of none returne, euerye suche sherife for the time being shall lose and forfait .v. li. the one halfe thereof shalbe to our Soueraigne Lord the king, his heires and successours: the other halfe to any such persone or persons as wil sue for the same in an accion of debt grounded vpon this acte, in any of the kinges courtes of recorde, wherein no essoygne, proteccion, or wager of lawe shalbe allowed, or admitted.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies this acte, or any thing therein conteined, shal not in any wise extend, or be preiudicial to the same countyes of Wales, or to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saide counties Palantine of Chester, or of the citie of Chester, for, or concerning such liberties, franchises, or priuileges, as belong to thē, or any of them, or to any ministers, or officers of them, or anye of them, otherwise, or in any other maner, then by the true meanīg of this act is before prouided &amp; declared: any thing in this act mencioned to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thys act, ne any thing therin conteined, shal not in any wise be preiudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, or hurtefull to any Lorde marcher in Wales, but that they &amp; euery of them, and their heires, and the heires of euery of them shal and may haue like liberty, interest, and preeminence, as they, and euerye of them had, might, or ought to haue had before the making of this act, and as though this acte had neuer been had, ne made: anye thyng in this acte mencioned to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:150873:18"/>
            <head>¶ The .xi. Chapiter. An Acte for the repeale of a certaine statute made in the .xxviii. yere of the reigne of the late king of most famous memory Henry the .viii for reuoking of actes of Parliament.</head>
            <p>WHere in the Parlyament begonne at Westmynster the .xxviii. yere of the reigne of the late Kynge of famous memorye kyng Henry the eight, it was enacted by the aucthoritie of the saide Parliament, that if the Emperyall crowne of this Realme, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the decease of the saide late kyng, shoulde dyscende, come, or remain to the heires of oure said late Soueraign Lord, or to any person to be lymitted by his highnesse, as of verye ryght it must, and ought to doe accordyng to the lawes of this realme established for the same, the said heire, or suche persone beinge within the age of fower &amp; twenty yeres, &amp; that then any acte or actes of Parliament should happen to be made &amp; established in any parliamēt, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> then should be holden before such heire or heires, person or persons then being in possession of the sayd crowne should be of their full ages, of .xxiiii. yeres, that then euery such heire, or heires of our saide late soueraigne Lorde, or such person so possessed of the crowne being within the same age of .xxiiii. yeares, should haue ful power and aucthoritie at all times, after they should come to their said full ages of .xxiiii. yeres, by their letters patentes vnder the great seale of England to reuoke, adnul, &amp; repeale all and singuler such acts made &amp; established by their royal assentes, in any Parliament holden during y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time that they were within their said age of .xxiiii. yeares, their roiall assentes had to the same, during the time that they were within y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said age of .xxiiii. yeres or any acte, or actes therafter to be made, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary therof notwithstāding. And it was also enacted by the auctority aforesaide, that euery suche repeale, adnullacion, and reuocacion of any acte or actes that should be made and established, in any Parliamente holdē before the time that such heirs, or person possessed of the crowne should be of the said age of xxiiii. yeres should be as good and effectual, to all intents &amp; purposes, as though it hath ben done by the aucthority of Parliament, as in the saide acte is more plainly declared: Sith the makyng of which estatute, it hath pleased almightie GOD to take vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his mercye our saide late Soueraigne Lorde king Henry the eight, our now most gracious &amp; deare Soueraigne liege lord kyng Edward the .vi. his sonne &amp; heire (whose life God lōg preserue) now beīg aboue the age of .x. yeres &amp; vnder the age of .xi. yeres: during whose minority as the common wealth of his highnesse realme of England, &amp; Ireland as of all the dominions and countreis of the same, is, and moste necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ought to be prouided for, maintetned, and preserued: so is it the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall duitie of euery good, true, and louing subiecte, to applie him self with al his power and diligence, to studye, inuente, and practyse by all waies, meanes, and maners, for the conseruacion of the same. And for
<pb facs="tcp:150873:19"/> asmuche as for the preseruacion of the royal estate of our said souerain Lorde the king that now is, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> safegard and suerty of hys most royal persone, &amp; for the good tranquilitie, quietnes, rest, and peace of his sayd Realmes, countreis, dominions, and subiectes, aswel wholsome lawes &amp; statuts are to be ordeined, established, &amp; prouided, as also some lawes &amp; statutes to bee repealed &amp; adnulled, as the case shal require, accordīg to the disposicion of the people, whiche cannot take anye good effect, or successe, without actes &amp; prouisions of Parliamente to be made, before their ages of .xxiiii. yeres. And for that it should seme vnto all men, that the good intencion, meaning, &amp; purpose of the said late king, and of the makers of the sayde statute, was not, that good and wholsome lawes which should be made, prouided, and ordained for the good gouernāce of the Realmes and dominions abouesaide, during the time that anye kyng of this Realme should be within y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said age of .xxiiii. yeres shoulde from the time of the decease of the auncestor, or progenitor of any suche king, within the age of .xxiiii. yeres, at the time of the death of the saide auncestour, or progenitour, vntill the age of .xxiiii. yeares, of any suche king, be made, demed, and adiudged to be voide by any such letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, to al intentes &amp; purposes, as though they neuer had been made but that the saide actes, and euery of them, and all, and euery thynge, &amp; thinges vsed, committed, doone, suffered, or executed by aucthority of the same, should be good, auaylable, and perfit in the lawe: And that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saide reuocacion, adnullacion, &amp; repeale, should be taken to make voide the saide actes, and euery of them onely, from the time of the said reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, adnullacion and repeale, &amp; not otherwise: The cōtrary entende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and exposicion wherof, might otherwise, not onely discourage all subiectes during that time, and those yeres, to endeuour themselues, to and for the aduising, setting foorthe, and consenting to the making of good and wholsome lawes: but also shoulde cause the sayd subiects to adiudge and thinke themselues to liue for that time, vnder no manner of certaintie, or assuraunce of any positiue lawe, or statute during that time to be made, or prouided: Be it therefore enacted, by the king oure Souereigne Lorde, with thassent of the Lordes spiritual &amp; temporal, &amp; the commons in this present Parliament assembled, &amp; by the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the same, that the said act of parliament aboue recyted, made in the saide .xxviii. yeare of the reigne of the said late King, &amp; euery word, article, clause, matter, sentence, and thing therein specified &amp; conteined, shall by aucthoritie of this present Parliament, bee, to all intentes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struccions, and purposes, vtterly voide, adnulled, repeled, and of none effect, &amp; as though the same had neuer ben had ne made. Neuertheles to the entente the kinges Maiestie our Souereign lord may haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; aucthoritie, preeminence and prerogatiue at his full age of .xxiiii yeres, or at any time after, at his libertie and pleasure, to repeale al sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and actes of Parliament, aswel made in this present parliament
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150873:19"/> as hereafter in any other Parlament to be holden, before he shall accō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishe the sayde age of xxiiii. yeres, to be made or ordeined, according to the true intent and meaning of the makers of the sayde former statute.</p>
            <p>Be it further ordeyned and enacted by the aucthoritie of thys present Parlament, that our saide soueraigne lord the kyng that now is, at hys full age of xxiiii. yeres, or at any tyme after, and all and euerye heire and heires of the sayd late kyng, and other persone and persones, to whom the Emperial crowne of thys realme shal hereafter descend, come, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine by thappointment of the sayde late kyng, in that case prouided &amp; made, then being within the age of xxiiii. yeres, shall haue full power &amp; aucthoritie, by vertue of thys present acte, at all tymes, after he, or they shal come to hys, or their full age of xxiiii. yeres, by hys, or theire letters patentes, vnder the great Seale of Englande, to repeale all &amp; singular acte &amp; actes, or any of thē, as be, or shalbe made, or establyshed by hys or theire Royal assentes in any Parlament holden, or to be holden, during the tyme that he, or they was, were, or shalbe, within y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said age of xxiiii. yeres, other then thys present act of Parlament, and other then all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons graunted &amp; to bee graunted, within the said seueral ages of xxiiii. yeres, by auctoritie of Parlament, so that the same repeale be made and vsed in maner and fourme hereafter folowing, that is to say, that euery suche letters patentes of repeale shall conteine all suche actes, as shalbee repealed, and shalbe solemnely &amp; openly proclaimed in the kyngs courte of Chauncerie, betwene the houres of ix. &amp; xi. before noone at three seue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall dayes, in euery of two of the iiii. vsual termes to bee holden at west<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster, or els where withyn thys realme of Englande, &amp; also one time in euery countie of thys Realme, and in wales, at the seueral Assises to bee holden in the same seuerall counties, betwene like houres, and that then after xl. daies next after suche Proclamation, in all and euery place and countie aboue saide, so had and made, the sayde letters patentes of repeale to take their force, strength and effect, and not before, or from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other tyme or season, nor in any other maner or fourme. And that all and euery suche acte and actes, aswel made in thys Parlament, as here after to be made, within the sayde age of xxiiii. yeres, of our souereygne Lord the kynges maiestie that now is, as in the tyme of any of the sayd heire or heires, or other the saide persone or persones then beyng in pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of the Imperial crowne of this realme, &amp; vnder the age of xxiiii. yeres, shalbe good and effectuall to all intentes, constructions, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, vntill the sayde letters Patentes of repeale, Proclamations, and xl. dayes shalbe so had, made, runne, and past: and that all and euery act and actes, thing and thinges, vsed, had, committed, doen, suffred, or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the auctoritie of the sayde acte or actes, or anye of them, within any of the sayde ages of xxiiii. yeres, according to the purporte, tenor, &amp; effect of the sayde act or actes, or any of them, shalbe good and offectual for euer, the sayde repeale so to be made, in any wise notwithstanding, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:150873:20"/> that all and euery persone and persones, bodies politique and corporat, shall and may by the aucthoritie of thys present acte, from time to time, aswell after the sayde repeale as before, pleade, or allege, for his or their defence, excuse, indemnitie, profite, benefite, or aduantage, all and euery suche act or actes, or any of them so reuoked, adnulled, or repealed, or to bee reuoked, adnulled, or repealed, for, concerninge, or in anye wise tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching any thing or thynges had, vsed, graunted, suffered, possessed, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, doen, or accrued, by thauctoritie, sufferaunce, or force of the sayd acte and actes, or anye of them before the reuocation, adnullation, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealinge of the same, in suche and as ample maner and fourme, as if the sayd acte and actes so to be reuoked, adnulled, or repealed, and euery of them, had stand in hys and their full strength, force, and effect, and as yf the sayd act or actes had neuer ben reuoked, adnulled, or repealed: anye thyng in suche repeale conteined notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; be it also ordeyned &amp; enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that no kyng nor kynges of thys realme, shal haue aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, power, or prerogatiue, to repeale any acte of Parlament or estatute, that shalbe made in the tyme of anye kyng before the sayde age of xxiiii. yeres, other then such as be, or shalbe made in his owne tyme: any thing aboue mencioned to the contrarye in anye wise notwithstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An act for the repeale of certain statutes, concerning trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, felonies, &amp;c. ¶ The .xii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing being more godlye, more sure, more to bee wished &amp; desired betwixt a Prince, the supreme head and ruler, &amp; the subiectes, whose gouernour &amp; head he is, then on the princes parte, great clemencie and indulgencie, and rather to muche forgeuenesse &amp; remission of hys royal power, &amp; iuste punishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt; then exact seueritie &amp; iustice to be shewed: &amp; on the subiects behalfe that they shoulde obey rather for loue, and for the necessitie and loue of a kyng and Prince, then for feare of hys streight, and seuere lawes: yet suche times at some time commeth in the common wealth, that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary and expedient, for the repressing of the insolencie and vnrulines of men, and for the foreseeing and prouiding of remedies against rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, insurrection, or suche mischiefes (as god some tyme with vs displea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed for oure punishement doth inflicte and laye vpon vs, or the Deuill at Goddes permission to assaye the good and goddes elect, doth sowe, and sette emonges) the which almyghtie God, with hys helpe and mannes policie, hath alwayes been content and pleased to haue stayed, that shar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per lawes, as a harder bryddle should be made, to stay those men &amp; fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that might els be occasion, cause and aucthours of further inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, the which thing caused the prince of most famous memory, kyng Henry the eight, father to our said soueraigne Lord the kyng, and other hys hyghenes progenitours, with thassent of the nobles &amp; commons, at diuers Parlaments in theire seueral tymes holden, to make and enacte
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150873:20"/> certain lawes and statutes, which mighte seeme and appeare to men of exterior realmes, &amp; many of the kyngs maiesties subiects very streight, sore, extreme, &amp; terrible, although they wer then, when they were made not without great consideration &amp; pollicie, moued and established, and for the time to thaduoidaunce of further inconuenience, very expedient and necessary. But as in tempest or winter, one course, &amp; garment is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, in calme or warme wether, a more liberal rase, or lyghter gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both may, and ought to be folowed and vsed: so we haue seene di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers streight and sore lawes made in one Parlement, the tyme so requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring, in a more calme and quiet reigne of another prince, by the like auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and Parlament repealed and taken awaye. The whiche moste hyghe clemencie and Royall example of hys Maiesties most noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitours, the kyngs hyghenes of hys tender &amp; godly nature most geuē to mercy and loue of his Subiectes, willing to followe, and perceauing the hartie and syncere loue, that hys moste louing Subiectes, both the Lordes &amp; cōmons doth beare vnto hys hyghnesse, now in thys hys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties tēder age, willing also to gratifie the same therfore, and minding further to prouoke hys sayde subiectes with indulgencie and clemencie shewed on hys hyghnes behalfe, to more loue and kyndnes toward hys Maiestie (if it may be) and vpon trust that they will not abuse the same, but rather be encoraged thereby more faithfully, &amp; with more diligence (if it may bee) and care for hys Maiestie, to serue hys hyghnesse now in thys hys tender age, is contented and pleased, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seueritie of certain lawes here folowing be mitigated &amp; remitted: Be it therfore ordeined and enacted by the kyng our souereigne lord, with thassent of the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des spiritual and temporal, and of the cōmons in thys present parlamēt assembled, &amp; by the aucthoritie of the same, that from henceforthe, none acte, deede, or offence, being by acte of Parlament, or statute made trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or petit treason, by woordes, writing, cyphring, dedes, or otherwise whatsoeuer shalbe taken, had, demed, or adiudged to bee hygh treason, or petit treason, but onely such as be treason or petit treason, in, or by the acte of Parlamēt, or statute made in the xxv. yere of the reigne of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most noble kyng of famous memory kyng Edward the iii. touching, or cōcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning treason, or the declarations of treasons: &amp; suche offences as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after shall by thys present acte be expressed &amp; declared to bee treason, or petit treason, and none other, nor that any peynes of deathe, penaltie, or forfeyture in any wise insue, or be to any of the offendors, for the doyng or committing any treason, or petit treason, other then such as be in the said estatute made in the sayd xxv. yere of the reigne of the saide kynge Edward the iii. or by thys present estatute ordeined &amp; prouided: any act or actes of parlamēt, statute or statutes, had, or made at any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, or after the sayde xxv. yere of the reigne of the said late king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the third, or anye other declaration or matter, to the contrarye in anye wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150873:21"/>
            <p>And also bee it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that all actes of Parlament and estatutes, touching, mentioning, or in anye wise concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning religion or opinions, that is to say, aswell the Statute made in the first yere of the reigne of the kyngs noble progenitour kynge Richarde the second, and the statute made in the second yere of the reigne of king Henry the v. and the Statute also made in the xxv. yere of the reigne of kyng Henry the eight, concerning punishment and reformation of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques and lollardes, and euery prouision therein conteined, and the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made for thabolishement of diuersitie of opiniōs, in certain articles concerning Christian religion, commonly called the vi. articles made in the Parlament begonne at Westminster the xxviii. daye of Aprill, in the xxxi. yere of the reigne of the most noble and victorious Prince, of most famous memory kyng Henry the eight, father to oure most dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine lord the king that now is, and also thact of Parlament and sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made of the Parlament begon at Westminster the xvi. daye of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, in the xxxiii. yere of the reigne of the said late kyng Henry y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eight and after that proroged vnto the xxii. day of Ianuary, in the xxxiiii. yere of the reigne of the said late kyng Henry the eight, touching, mēcioning, or in any wise cōcerning bokes of thold and new testament in English, and the Printing, vttering, sellyng, geuing, or deliueringe of bookes, or writtinges, and reteining of English bookes or writings, and reading, preaching, teaching, or expounding of scripture, or in any wise touching, mencioning, or concerning any of the same matters. And also one other statute made in the parlament holden at Westminster, in the xxxv. yere of the reigne of the said late kyng Henry the eight, concerning the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of the statute of vi. articles, &amp; all &amp; euery other act or actes of parlament, concerning doctrine, or matters of religion, &amp; all and euery branche, article, sentence, and matter, peines &amp; forfeitures cōteined, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, or in any wise declared, in any of the same actes of parlament, or estatutes, shal frō hēceforth be repeled, &amp; vtterly voide &amp; of none effect.</p>
            <p>And bee it further ordeined and enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayd, that all offences made felony, by any acte or actes of parlament, statute, or statutes, made sithens the xxiii. daye of Aprill, in the firste yere of the reigne of the sayd late kyng Henry the eight, not being felony before, &amp; also, all and euery the braunches and articles mentioned, or in any wise declared, in any of the same statutes, concerning the makyng of any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or offences, to be felony, not being felony before: and all peynes &amp; forfeitures, concerning the same, or anye of them, shal from henceforthe be repealed, and vtterly voide and of none effect.</p>
            <p>And bee it also ordeyned &amp; enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that one acte made in the Parlament holden at Westminster, in the xxxi. yere of the reigne of the sayd late kyng Henry the eight, that proclamacions made by the kyngs hyghnesse, by the aduise of hys honorable counsaile, shoulde bee obeyed and kepte, as though they were made by aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150873:21"/> of a parlament: and also one other act made in the Parlament holdē in the xxiiii. yere of the reigne of the said late king Henry the eight, for the due execution of the said proclamations, &amp; also all &amp; euery braunche, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle &amp; matter in the same statutes, &amp; euery of thē mēcioned or declared shal from hencefoorth be repealed, and vtterly voide, and of none effect.</p>
            <p>And bee it enacted by thaucthoritie aforesayde, that yf any persone or persones, at any tyme after the firste daye of Marche next comming, by open preaching, expresse words or sayinges, do affirme, or set forth, that the kyng, hys heires or successoures kynges of this realme for the time being is not, or ought not to bee supreme head in earth of the Church of England and Ireland, or any of them, immediately vnder God, or that the bishop of Rome, or any other person or persons, other then the kyng of Englande for the time being is, or ought to bee by the lawes of God, supreme head of the same churchs, or of any of thē, or that the kyng, his heires or successoures kyngs of thys realme, is not, or ought not to bee kyng of England, Fraunce and Ireland, or of any of them, or after the sayd first day of Marche, doe compasse or imagine by open preachinge, expresse woordes, or sayinges, to depose or depriue the kyng, hys heirs; or successours kyngs of thys realme, from hys, or theire Royal estate, or titles, to, or of the realmes aforesayd, or doe openly publishe, or say by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse wordes or sayinges, that any other persone, or persons, other thē the kyng, hys heirs or successours kynges of thys realme, of right ought to be kyngs of the realmes aforesaid, or any of them, or to haue &amp; enioy the same, or anye of them: that then euerye suche offendor being thereof duely conuicted, or attainted by the lawes of thys realme, their aidors, cōforters, abbettors, procurours, and counsailours, for his or their such first offence, shall lose and forfayte to the kyng, all hys &amp; theire goodes, and cattalles, and also shall haue &amp; suffre imprisonement, of hys &amp; theyr bodies, at the kyngs will and pleasure. And if any persone beyng oure conuicted or attainted of anye of the sayde offences, shall after hys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiction or attaindour eftsones commit or perpetrate any of the offences before mentioned, other then such as be expressed in the sayde estatute, made in the sayde xxv. yere of kyng Edwarde the iii. and shalbe thereof duely cōuicted or attainted by the lawes of this realme: that then euery such offendor, their aidors, coūforters, abbettours, procurours and coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saylors, for his, or their said second offence or offences, shall lose and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte to the kyng, the whole issues and profites of all hys &amp; their lādes, tenementes, &amp; other hereditamentes, benefices, prebendes, &amp; other spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual promotions, for terme of life, of suche offendour or offendoures: &amp; shall also lose and forfayte to the kyng all his and their goodes and cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, and also suffre, during hys and their lifes, perpetual imprisonmēt of his and their bodies. And if anye persone being two tymes hereafter conuicted or attainted of any of the same offences, shall after his said se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond conuiction or attainder, eftsons commit or perpetrate again any of
<pb facs="tcp:150873:22"/> the said offences to be therof duely conuicted or attainted by the lawes and statutes of thys realme: that then euery such third offence or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, shalbe demed and adiudged hygh treason, and the offendor or offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dors, their aidors, comfortors, abbettours, procurours, &amp; counsailours, being therin conuicted or attainted, according to the lawes &amp; statuts of thys realme, shalbe deemed and adiudged hyghe traitours, &amp; shal suffre peines of deathe, and lose and forfaite all theire goodes and cattalles, landes and tenementes, to the kyng, as in cases of hygh treason.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayd, that if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone or persones, at any time after the sayd first day of March next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, by writing, printing, ouert deede or acte, doe affirme, or sett forth, that the kyng of thys realme for the tyme being, is not, or ought not to be supreme head in earth of the churche of England and Ireland, or of any of thē, immediately vnder God: or shall, by writing, printing, ouert deede, or acte, after the sayd first daye of Marche, affirme, or set forth, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the bishop of Rome, or any other person or persons, other then the kyng of Englande for the time being, is, or ought to be by the lawes of God, or otherwise, the supreme head in earth of the same churches, or of anye of them: or do after the said first day of March, compasse, or imagine by writing, printing, ouert deede or acte, to depose or depriue the kyng, hys heires or successours kyngs of thys realme, frō his, or their royal estate, or titles of the kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, or of anye of them: or by any writing, printing, ouert dede, or acte, do affirme, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> any other persone or persons, other then the kyng, hys heirs and successours is, or of right ought to be king of the realmes of Englande, Fraunce, or Ireland, or to haue and enioy the same, or any of them: that then euery suche offence and offences, shalbe demed and adiudged hyghe treason, &amp; thoffendour &amp; offendours, their aidours, cōforters, abbettors, {pro}curers, and counsailours therin cōuicted or attainted, according to the lawes &amp; statutes of thys realme, shalbe demed and adiudged hyghe traitours, &amp; shal suffre peines of death, &amp; lose &amp; forfeit al theire goodes and cattales, landes and tenementes, to the kyng, as in cases of hyghe treason.</p>
            <p>Prouided always, &amp; be it enacted by thauctoritie aforesayd, that this estatute, or any thing therein conteined, shal not in anye wise extende to repell, adnulle, or make frustrate or voyde, anye acte or actes of Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, statute or statutes made, concerninge the counterfeytinge, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geing of any of the coynes of thys Realme, or for the coyne of any other realme or realmes, currāt within this realme, or for clipping, washinge, or filing anye of the sayd coines, or for, or concerninge the bringing into thys realme, of counterfaite money or coyne: ne to anye statute made in the xxvii. yere of the said late kyng Henry the eight, concerning the false forgeing and counterfeyting of the kynges sygnes Manuell, priuie sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, or priuie seale, ne to their counsailours, procurors, aidours, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettours, nor to any article or braunche concerning the same offences, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150873:22"/> any of them conteined in the same statutes, or any of them.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayd, that if any the heires of the king our said souereigne lord that now is, or anye persone or persones, to whom the crowne and dignitie of this realme is limited and appointed by act of parlament, made in the xxxv. yere of the reigne of the said late kyng Henry the eight, or the heires of any of them doe at any time herafter, vsurpe the one of them vpon the other, in the crowne of this realme, or demaūde, challēge, or claime the same, otherwise, or in any other fourme or degre of discent or succession, or in any other course, fourme, degree, or cōdition, but onely in suche maner &amp; fourme, as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the said estatute: or if any of the saide heires, or persons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, do interrupt, or let the kyngs hyghnesse that now is, peaceablye &amp; quietly to kepe, haue, and enioy the sayd imperial Crowne: that then, all &amp; singular the offendors, their aidors, conforters, abbettors, procurors, and counsailors therein, shalbe demed and adiudged hygh traitors, and shall suffre and incurre the peines of death, losse and forfeitures, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresayd, in cases of hyghe treason.</p>
            <p>And it is further ordeyned &amp; enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that no person or persons, that heretofore hath been, or at any tyme her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after shalbe, in due fourme of the lawes attainted or cōuicted of murder or malice prepensed, or of poisoning of malice prepensed, or of breakynge of any house by day or by night, any persone being then in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same house, where the same breaking heretofore hath been, or hereafter shalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and heretofore hath been, or herafter shalbe, thereby put in feare or dreade, or of, or for robbing of any person or persons in the high way, or nere to the high waye, or for felonious stealing of horses, geldynges, or mares; or of felonious taking of any goodes out of any parish church or other churche, or chappel, or being indicted or appealed of anye of the same offences, and thereupon found gyltie by verdict of xii. men, or shall confesse the same, vpon hys or their arreignement, or will not aunswere directly, according to the lawes of this realme, or shal stande wilfully, or of malice mute, shall not bee admitted to haue or enioye the priuilege or benefite of hys clergie or Sanctuary, but shalbe put from the same: and that in all other cases of felonie, other then suche as before mentioned, all and singuler persone &amp; persones, which after the first daye of March next comming, shalbe arreigned or founde gyltie, vpon his or their arrei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gnement, or shal confesse the same, or stand mute in fourme aforesayd, or will not aunswere directly in fourme abouesaid, shal haue and enioy the priuilege and benefite of his or their clergie, the libertie and priuilege of Sanctuarye, in like maner and fourme, as he or they might, or shoulde haue doen, before the xxiiii. day of April, in the firste yere of the reigne of the sayd late kyng Henry the eight.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by the auctoritie aforesayde, that all clauses, articles, and sentences, mentioned, or specified in any acte or
<pb facs="tcp:150873:23"/> actes of parlament, statute or statutes made in the tyme of the reigne of the sayde late kyng Henry the eight, touching, or in any wise concerning any maner of challenge, for the Countie, Hundred, or peremptory chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, or any of them, or touching, or in any wise concerning any maner of triall of forein plees pleded by murtherers, felons, or other offendors shall, as cōcerning the said challenges and trials, remaine in theire force and strength not repealed, any thing in thys act mentioned, sounding or seming to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it ordeyned and enacted by the auctoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, that thys act of parlament, or any thing therin mēcioned as cōcer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning the repeale of anye estatute or estatutes made touching treason, or misprision of treason, shal not in any wise geue any maner of benefit, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage, or commoditie, to any persone or persones, being the last day of Octobre laste past, arrestest, or imprisoned for treason, petit treason, or misprision of treason, or to any person or persons heretofore being indic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of treason, petit treason, or misprision of treason, or to any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone or persons being likewise conuicted, outlawed, or attainted of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, petit treason, or misprision of treason: or beyng fled beyond the seas, or into Scotlande, before the sayde laste daye of Octobre laste paste, for any treason, petit treason, or misprision of treason: but that they &amp; euery of them, shal suffre suche peines of death, losses and forfeitures of landes and goodes, as in cases of treason, as though thys acte had neuer been had or made: any thing in thys acte to the cōtrarie in any wise notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing: &amp; that the lawes &amp; statutes repealed by thys act shall stand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thē: &amp; euery of thē, in full strength, vertue, force and effect, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all &amp; euery offence by thē, or any of thē, hertofore cōmitted or doen.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it ordeined and enacted, by the auctoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, that all wilfull killinge, by poisoning of anye persone or persones, that at anye time hereafter shalbe doen, perpetrated, or committed, shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be adiudged, takē, and demed wilful murders of malice prepensed: and that the offendors therin, their aidors, abbettours, procurours, &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sailours, shall suffre death, and forfait in euery behalfe, as in other cases of wilfull murder of malice prepensed.</p>
            <p>And ouer that, bee it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that in all and euery case and cases, where any of the kynges Maiesties subiectes shall &amp; maye vpon hys prayer, haue the priuilege of clergie, as a Clerke conuict, that may make purgation in all those cases, and euery of them, and also in all and euery case and cases of felony, wherein the priuilege and benefite of clergie is restreined, excepted, or takē away by thys esta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tute, or acte, (wilful murder, and poysoning of malice prepensed, onelye excepted) the Lorde and lordes of the parlament, and pere and peres of the realme hauing place and voyce in parlament, shall by vertue of thys present acte of common grace, vpon hys, or theire request or praier, alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging thathe is a Lorde, or pere of this realme, &amp; claiminge the benefite
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150873:23"/> of thys act, though he cānot reade, without any burning in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hand, losse of inheritaunce, or corruption of hys bloud, be adiudged, dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, taken, &amp; vsed, for hys first tyme onely, to all intentes, cōstructions, &amp; purposes, as a clerke conuict, &amp; shall in case of a clerke conuict, whiche maye make purgation, without any further or other benefite or priuilege of clergie, to any such Lorde or pere, frō thenceforth at any tyme after, for any case to be allowed, adiudged, or admitted: any lawe, statute, vsage, custome, or any other thing to the contrary, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that if anye of the sayde Lordes of the parlament, or any of the peres of thys realme for the time being, shal fortune to bee indicted of any of the offences limitted in thys act: that thē they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> entry of them, shal haue hys or their triall by their peeres, as it hath been vsed heretofore, in cases of hygh treason.</p>
            <p>And bee it further enacted by the auctoritie aforesayd, that yf any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone or persones, that by thys statute, or by any other statutes or lawes of thys realme ought to haue, or bee admitted, to the benefite of hys, or their clergie: that the same persone and persones, shalbe from hēceforth admitted &amp; allowed, to hys or their clergie, although they, or any of thē, haue ben diuers &amp; sundrye times maried, to any single woman, or single women, or to anye widowe, or widowes, or to two wiues, or mo: anye law, statute, or vsage, to the contrarye in anye wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And ouer that, it is ordeyned and enacted by the auctoritie aforesaide, that albeit any persone, or persones, of what estate, cōdiciō, or degree, he or they be, shal hereafter fortune to be attainted, conuicted, or outlawed of anye treason, petit treason, misprision of treason, murder, or Felonye whatsoeuer, yet that notwithstanding, euery womā, that is, or shall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to bee wife of the persone so attainted, conuicted, or outlawed, shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be endowable and enable to demaunde, haue, and enioye her dower, in like maner and fourme, as though her husband had not been attainted, conuicted, or outlawed: any statute, lawe, vsage, or custome, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye in any wise notwithstanding. Sauing to all and euery other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone and persones, bodies politike and corporate, theire heires and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, and to euery of them, other then to such offendour or offendours as shalbe attainted, conuicted, or outlawed, all such right, title, interest, entree, leases, possession, condition, profit, commoditie, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, as they or any of them had, or should, or of right ought to haue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or at the time of the sayd attainder, conuiction, or outlagarie.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted, by the auctoritie aforesayde, that one acte made at the Parlament holden at Westminster, vpon diuers proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, the iiii. day of February, in the xxvii. yere of the sayd late kynge Henry the eighte, and there continued and kept, vntill the xxiiii. daye of Aprill then next ensuing, concerning and touching the felonious taking awaye by anye seruaunt, the goodes or cattalles, of the maister or mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse, and all Articles and Sentences conteyned in the same acte, shall
<pb facs="tcp:150873:24"/> stande, be, and remaine in full strength, force, and effecte, in suche maner and fourme, as it did before the making of thys present act, the repeael, or reuocation of the acts abouesayde, to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by the auctoritie abouesaid, that no persone or persones shal in any wise be impeched, or put to aunswere for any of thoffences abouesaid, cōcerning treasons, by open preaching, or wordes onely, vnlesse the partie offendor or offendors bee thereof ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused within xxx. dayes next after the same opē preaching, or wordes so spoken or declared, if thaccusours shal fortune to be within thys realme, during the sayde space of xxx. dayes, next after the sayd offence cōmitted or doen. And if the accusors shal happen to be out of this realme, during the said space of xxx. daies: then the partie or parties so offending, shalbe accused, as is aforesayde, within sixe monethes, next after the same prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, or wordes spoken or declared: or els the partie or parties so offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, their aidors, comforters, abbettours, and counsailours, or anye of thē not to be empeached, or put to aunswere for any such offence, or offē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the same accusation, or accusatiōs so to be had, made, &amp; declared, shalbe made to one of the kyngs counsaile, or to one of the kyngs Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Assise, or els to one of the kynges Iustices of peace beynge of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> or to two Iustices of the peace, within the Shyre, where the same offence or offences shal happen to be doen or committed: any thing cōteyned in thys act to the cōtrary therof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, &amp; bee it declared and enacted by the aucthoritie aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, that concelement, or keping secrete anye high treason, shalbe from henceforth adiudged, demed, &amp; taken, misprision of treason, &amp; the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor therein shall forfayte and suffre, as in cases of misprision of treason, as heretofore hath been vsed: any thyng aboue mencioned to the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, &amp; be it declared &amp; enacted by the auctoritie abouesaid, that thys acte or any thing therein conteyned, shall not extende to char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, or make any persone or persones to bee offendor or offendors, in any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> articles abouesaid, for calling, naming, saying, writing, or printinge the Frenche kyng, for the tyme beyng, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of the kyng of Fraūce or Frenche kyng, any thing aboue declared and enacted, to the contrary in anye wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and bee it enacted by the auctoritie aforesayd, that no persone or persones, after the firste daye of Februarye next comming shalbe indicted, arreygned, condemned, or conuicted, for anye offence of treason, petit treason, misprision of treason, or for anye woordes before specified, to bee spoken after the sayd firste daye of February, for whiche the same offendoure, speaker, offendours, or speakers, shall in anye wise suffre any peynes of death, imprisonment, losse, or forfeiture of his goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, cattalles, landes or tenementes: vnlesse the same offendor, speaker, offendours, or speakers bee accused by two sufficient and lawefull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150873:24"/> as shall willingly without violence confesse the same.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An act for a Subsidie of tonnage &amp; poundage of merchaundise, with a prouiso for the confirmation of the Priuileges of the merchauntes of the Styliard, which prouiso shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce but onely to thende of thys Parlament. ¶ The .xiii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N their most humble wise shewen vnto your most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maiestie, your poore cōmons in thys your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent parlament assembled, that wher aswel your most dearest father of famous memorie kyng Henry y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> viii. as also your most worthy graundfather kyng Hēry y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vii. &amp; other your noble {pro}genitours kings of this your realme of Englād, time out of minde, haue had, graū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them, &amp; enioyed of the cōmons of the same realme, for the tyme being, by auctoritie of parlamēt, for the defence of the same nowe youre realme, &amp; the keping &amp; safegarde of the seas for thētercourse of merchā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise, safely to come into the same youre Realme, &amp; to passe out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, certain sommes of money, named subsidies, of all maner of gooddes and merchaūdises, cōming in, or going out of the same your realme: &amp; foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as we your said poore cōmōs haue {per}ceiued your Maiesties good fauour &amp; will towards vs your said poore cōmons, had aswel in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of vs, &amp; this your realme, against your rebels the Scottes, as also the keping &amp; sure defending of the Seas, against all persons intending the disturbance &amp; inuasion of thys your realme, &amp; vs your said cōmōs to our great cōfort &amp; reioising, as cause requireth, &amp; to your maiestie great costes, charges, &amp; expences, &amp; also not doubting the sequele of the same if nede shall require: We therfore your said poore cōmons, as bounden of duetie, humbly desire your excellēt Maiestie benignely &amp; fauourably to take, accept, &amp; receiue these our poore graūts herafter ensuing, as graū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of true hartes &amp; good willes, which we beare to your hyghenes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes your said great costes, charges &amp; expences, aswel heretofore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended &amp; laid out, as herafter by your Maiestie for the causes aforesaid, whē nede shal require, to be expēded &amp; laid out, as the first fruits of our good willes &amp; hartes toward your highnesse, although the same doe, or herafter shal nothing in effect counteruaile your saide costes, charges, &amp; expēces, which we be not able fully to gratifie by any meanes. First, we your poore cōmons, by the aduise &amp; assent of the Lords spiritual &amp; tēpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, in thys youre present Parlament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, to thintent aforesaid, geue and graunt to you oure said So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne Lord, one subsidie called tonnage, that is to saye, of euery tōne of wine comming, or that shal, or is come into thys your realme, by way of merchādise, the summe of iii.s. &amp; so after the rate: &amp; of euery tonne of swete wine, aswel malmesey as other that shall, or is come into the same your realme, by euery or any merchant alien, aswel by the merchaūts of
<pb facs="tcp:150873:25"/> Haunse and Almayne, as by any other merchant straunger, of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion soeuer he bee iii.s. and so after the rate, ouer &amp; aboue the iii.s. afore graunted. And of euery awlne of Renishe wine comming, or that shal, or is come into thys your realme, by way of merchaundise, by euery, or any merchaunt, denizen, or alien, of what nation soeuer he be xii.d. And also one other subsidie, called pōdage, that is to saye, of all maner of goodes and merchaundises, of euerye Marchaunt, Denizen and alien whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he be, caried, &amp; to be caried, out of this your said realme, or brought or to be brought into the same by waye of merchaūdises of the value of euery .xx.s. of the same goodes and merchaundises xii.d. and so after the rate. And of xx.s. value of Tinne and Pewter vessell caried oute of thys your realme by any and euery merchaūt alien xii.d. ouer and aboue the xii.d. aforesaid. Except alwayes and forprised out of thys graunt of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidie of poundage, all maner of wollen cloth made and wrought, or that shalbe made and wrought within thys realme of England, &amp; by euerye, or anye merchaunte denizen and not borne alien, caried or to bee caried out of thys your saide realme, and all maner of wolle, wolle felles, &amp; hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and barkes of Lether also caried, or to be caried out of thys your re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alme, and all wines, and all maner of freshe fishe and bestial, comming, or that is, or shal come into the same your realme.</p>
            <p>And further, we your sayde poore commons by the aduise, assent, and aucthoritie aforesayd, geue and graunt vnto you our said Souereigne Lorde, for the causes aboue rehearsed, one other Subsidie of all maner of wolle, wolle felles, &amp; lether caried, or to be caried out of this your real<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, in maner and fourme folowing, that is to say of euery merchant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizen of, &amp; for euery sacke of woll xxxiii.s.iiii.d. And of euery cc.xl. wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felles .xxxiii.s. iiii.d. And of, and for euerye laste of hydes and backes, of euery suche merchaunt denizen .iii. li. vi.s. viii.d. And also of euerye mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt straunger not borne your liege man, aswell those that bee made denizens, as hereafter shalbe made by letters patentes or otherwise, as all other merchaunt straungers, of, and for euery sacke of wolle .iii. li. vi. s. viii.d. And, of, &amp; for euerye .cc.xl. wollefelles .iii. li. vi.s. viii.d. And also of euery last of hydes and backes .iii. li. xiii.s. iiii.d. And so of all the said wolles, wollefelles, hydes &amp; backes, &amp; euery of them, after the rate that so is, or shalbe caried, to haue, take, enioye, and perceaue the subsidies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaide, &amp; euery of thē, &amp; euery part or parcel of them to your hyghnes from the first daye of your most noble reigne, during your lyfe natural.</p>
            <p>And further, we your sayde poore commons most humblye desire your Maiestie, that it may be enacted by your hyghnesse, by the aduise &amp; assēt of the Lordes aforesayde, and vs your sayde commons, and by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde auctoritie of thys present Parlament assembled, that the giftes &amp; grauntes aforesayde, shalbee good and effectual, accordinge to the true meaning of the same. And that it may be further enacted by the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie aforesayde, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> yf any wines, goodes, merchaundises, wolles, wolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felles,
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:150873:25"/> hydes, &amp; backes of leather aforesaide, or other thyngs afore spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed wherof the subsidies aforesaid, or any of them, is or shalbe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after due, shall at any time hereafter, during the time aforesaid, be ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped or put into any boate, craier, ship or vessel, to that intent to be cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the partes of beyond the sea, or els be brought from the partes of beyōd the sea, into any port, hauē, creeke, or other place of this your realme by way of marchandise and there laide on lande, the Subsidye aforesaid of the same (due or to be due by reason of this graūt) not pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or the collectour of the same Subsidy not agreed with for the same according to the true meanyng and intent of these aforesaid grauntes, and euery of them: that then from the first day of March next cōmyng and not before, al the said wines, goods, merchaundises, woolles, wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felles, hides and backes, and other the premisses aforesaide, and euerye parte and parcel therof so shipped or els put into any boate, craier, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vessel afore saide, to thintent afore said, or brought into this realme and there laid on land, as is also aforesaid, shal remaine forfait to your highnes, during the time aforesaid: the one moity thereof, or the value therof to your highnesse, and the other moyty to him or them that shall sease the same or sue for the same. And that it may please your highnes that al marchaunts aswell Denizons as straungers, coming into thys your realme, be well &amp; honestly intreated &amp; demeaned, as they were in the time of your aforesaid noble progenitors wythout oppressiō to thē to be done, paying the Subsidies abouesaid.</p>
            <p>And ferther, that it be enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny goods, merchaūdises, wolles, wollfelles or leather aforesaid, or any part therof of any merchaunt denizon, naturally borne your liege man, which shall passe out of this your said realme, after the said first day of Matche, during the terme of this giftes and graunt, shal happen to be taken with enemies of pirates vppon the sea, or perished by misfortune in any ship or ships, that shal happen to be taken or peryshed within the time of the said graunt, wherof the Subsidies aforesaid or anye of thē to your highnes due or to be due, is, or shal be in forme aforesaid duely payed or agreed for without fraude or collusion, and such losse or losses as ben before rehearsed, be found and proued before the Treasorer of England, or the chiefe Baron of our Eschequer for the time being, by the examinacion of the same merchaunts if they be on liue, or of theire executours or administrators, if they be dead, or two true credible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons sworne, or other reasonable witnes &amp; profes sworne, wytnessinge the same merchaūdises so to be lost or perished: that then the same mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunts denizons that were or shalbe owners of the aforesayd goods merchauntes, woolle, wollfelles, hydes or other merchaundises afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, as shall be so perished or lost, if they be on liue, or their executours and admynystratours, if they bee dead, and euerye of them, by force and vertue of this acte when them liketh, duringe the said terme, shall
<pb facs="tcp:150873:26"/> moue ship asmuche wolle, wollefelles, hides or other marchaūdise in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same porte or ports, in whiche the same woll, wollfelles, hides, or other goods and marchaundises aforesayd, so lost &amp; perished, were or shall be shipped without any of the subsidies aforesayd now graūted, to be had or paied therfore to you in any wise, and that al such profites of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses so to be lost or perished, be certifyed into your Chaūcery, by your said treasorer or chief Baron, there to remaine of record, and after such certificat made the Chauncellor of England, or the Lord keper of your great seale, for the time being, do make and deliuer vnto the said mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes, their executors or administrators, or any of them, or to their attorney or to their attorneis in that behalfe, or any of them, as manye and suche writtes and warranties to be directed as well to the collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the subsidies aforesaid, or any, or euery of them for the time be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, as to the treasorer &amp; barons of your Eschequer for the time beyng as shalbe requisite and nedeful for the said merchaūts, their executors or administratours or their attorney or attorneys, or any of thē, or the saide collectors or any of them, to haue for the obtayning, aswel of the shipping, as of allowance therof: And ferther that euery marchaūt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizen that shal ship hereafter any woll, wollfelles, hides, or anye other gooddes &amp; marchaundises in any carricke or galley, shall paye to your Maiestie during the time aforesaide, all maner of customes and al the subsidies aforesaide, as any alien borne out of this your realme.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that no acte, statute, or ordinaunce had, made or to be made in this present Parlament, be in any wise hurtfull or preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial vnto the merchaunts of the Hause in Almaine, hauing the house in the citie of London, comonly called <hi>Guilhalda Theutonicorum,</hi> nor to any fraunchises, liberties or priuileges to them or their predecessors before this time had, agreed, graunted or confirmed, nor to any lawful vsages by them or by their predecessors before this time vsed, but that the saide merchauntes and their successors haue, holde, and enioye, all their saide fraunchises, libertyes, and free vsages, accordynge to suche grauntes, confirmacions and agrementes, as by the kynge and his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble progenitors kinges of Englande haue beene agreed, made &amp; graū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and had to the said merchaunts or theire predecessours, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their lawfull vsages in euery thing, by whatsoeuer other name or names, the same merchaūts, or any of them be called, or named: any acte, statute, or ordinaunce made or to be made in this present Parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the contrary notwithstanding: This present prouiso to endure and continue vnto the ende of this present parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .xiiii. Chapiter. ¶ An acte whereby certaine Chaunteries, Colleges, free chappelles, and the possessions of the same, be geuen to the kyngs Maiestie.</head>
            <pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:150873:26"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He kinges most louing subiects, the lordes Spiritual &amp; temporal, &amp; the cōmons in this present parliamente assembled, considering y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a great part of supersticyō &amp; errours in Christian religion, hath been brought into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mindes &amp; estimaciō of men, by reason of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ignorance of their very true &amp; perfit saluaciō, through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> death of Iesus Christ, &amp; by deuising &amp; phātasiyng vain opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of purgatorie, &amp; masses satisfactorie, to be done for them, which be departed: The which doctrine &amp; vain opiniō, by nothyng more is maī<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined and vpholden then by the abuse of Trentalles, Chauntries, and other prouisions made for the continuaunce of the saide blindnesse and ignoraunce. And ferther considering and vnderstanding that the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion, chaunge, &amp; amendement of the same, &amp; conuerting to good and godly vses, as in erecting Grāmer Scholes to the educacion of youth in vertue and godlines, the further augmenting of the Vniuersities, &amp; better prouision for the poore and needie, cannot in this presente Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamente be prouided, and conuenientlye done, nor cannot, ne oughte to anye other maner persone be committed, then to the Kinges highnesse, whose Maiestie, with, and by the aduise of his highnes most prudente Counsaile, can &amp; wil most wisely, and beneficially bothe for the honour of God, and the weale of his Maiesties Realme, order, alter, conuerte, and dispose the same. And calling furder to their remembraunce that in the Parlament holden at Westminster the, xxxvii. yeare of the reigne of our late Soueraigne Lorde kynge Henrye the eighte, father to our moste dreade and natural Soueraigne Lorde the kynge, that now is it was ordeined, enacted, and established emongst other thynges, that al &amp; singuler Colleges, free Chappelles, Chauntries, Hospitalles, Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternities, Brotherheddes, Guildes, and other promocions, mencioned in the saide former act, had, or made to haue continuance in perpetuitie for euer, and then being, or that hadde, or ought to bee contributorie or chargeable to the payment of the first fruites and tenthes, accordynge to the lawes and statutes in that behaulfe hadde, and made by what name, surname, degree, or corporaciō, they, or any of thē were founded ordeined, established, erected, named, called, or knowen: and al and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler the mansion houses, manours, orchardes, gardens, landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, pastures woods, waters, rentes, reuercions, seruices, cōmons, tythes, pencions, porcions, churches, chappelles, aduowsons, nomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions, patronages, annuities, rightes, interestes, entrees, condiciōs leetes, courtes, liberties, priuileges, fraunchises, &amp; other hereditamēts whatsoeuer, then apperteining, or belonging, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> did appertain, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, or were assigned, or appointed to anye suche colledge, free chapel chauntrye, hospital, fraternitie, brotherhed, guilde, stypendiare prycste or other the saide promocions, or to any of thē, or accepted, knowen, or takē as part, parcel, or member of them, or of any of them: &amp; to the said
<pb facs="tcp:150873:27"/> Colleges, chauntryes, free chappelles, hospytalles, fraternytyes, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhed, guylde, stipendarie pryestes, or other promocions, or to any of thē vnited, or annexed: which betwene the .iiii. day of February, in the xxvii. yere of the saide late kings reigne, &amp; the .xxv. day of December in the .xxxvii. of his graces reigne, by reason of any entree, expulsion, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, sale, feoffement, fine, recouerie, leasse, or other conueighance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made, were dissolued, determined, or relinquished by any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> waies meanes, or conueighaunces, mencioned in the saide acte, or otherwyse other then such of them, as then were in the possessyon of the saide late king, or that weee graunted, or assured by his licence, agrement, cōsent or letters patents, to any person or persons, or then had ben lawfullye obteined, or recouered by any person, by any former right, or title, with out fraude or couin, or by the kyngs licence, shal frō thenceforth by auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the same former acte, be adiudged &amp; demed, &amp; also bee in the very actual and real possession &amp; seison of the saide late king, and of his heires and successours for euer: in as large &amp; ample maner, as the saide priestes, wardens, masters, ministers, gouernours, rulers, or other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents, or any of them, or the patrons, donours, or foundours of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them at any time sithens the said fowerth day of February in the xxvii. yere aforesayd, had, occupied, or enioyed, or then had, occupied, or enioyed the same, &amp; as though all and singuler the said colleges, chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, hospitalles, free chappelles, fraternities, brotherheddes, guildes and other the saide promocions, and the saide manours, Landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, hereditamentes, and other the premisses, whatsoeuer they be, &amp; euery of them, had been in the said former acte, specially, particulerly, &amp; certaynly rehearsed, named, &amp; expressed by expresse woordes, names, surnames, corporaciōs, titles, and faculties, and in their natural kinds and qualities: the saide entrees, expulsions, bargaines, sales, fynes, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offements, recoueries, or other assurance, and conueyghaunce whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they were, had, or made (except before in the former act excepted) to the contrary notwithstanding. And where also it was enacted and graunted by the saide late king, by the saide former acte, that the same late king during his natural lyfe, might make and direct his commissiō and commissions vnder his great seale, to entre into al &amp; singuler suche and as manye chauntryes, free chappelles, hospytalles, colleges, and other the promocions mencioned in the saide former acte, &amp; into al and singuler suche manours, mansions, houses, measses, lands, tenements, pastures, wooddes, waters, rentes, reuercions, seruices, possessions, &amp; other heredytaments whatsoeuer, or into any parte, or parcell thereof in the name, season, and possessyon of all the hereditamentes, annexed, vnited, belonging, or apperteining to any chauntry, hospital, free chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, college, fraternytie, brotherhed, guilde, or other the saide promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, or wherof any priestes, prouostes, gouernours, rulers, or other incumbentes, of them, or any of them, by what name, surname, degree,
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:150873:27"/> title, or corporacion, they, and euery of them, or anye of them were foū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, erected, ordeined, established, named, called, or knowē, then had or enioyed, or that hereafter should haue, or enioye to the said chauntries hospitalles, free chappelles, colledges, fraternityes, brotherheds, guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or other the saide promocions that then were chargeable to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the first fruites, and tenthes: &amp; all colleges that were chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or not chargeable to the said payment of the first fruites &amp; tenthes as is aforesaide, or to any of them, as should be named, expressed &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the sayde commission or commissions: and to seise and take the same chauntries, hospitalles, colleges, free chappelles, fraternities, brotherheddes, guildes, and other the saide promocions, manors, lāds tenementes, and other the premisses mencioned in the saide commissy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or commissyons, and in euery of them, and euerye parte, parcell, and member of the same into the kinges possession and handes, to haue and to holde the same to the saide late king, and to hys heires &amp; successors, for euer, as by the saide former act emongst other things more at large appeareth: it is now ordeyned and enacted by the king our soueraigne Lorde with the assent of the lordes and commons in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament assembled, and by the aucthoritie of the same, that al maner of colleges, free chappelles, and chauntries, hauing, being, or in <hi>esse,</hi> with-fiue yeares nexte before the firste daye of this presente Parlyamente, which were not in actual and reall possessyon of the saide late king, nor in the actual and real possession of the kyng our soueraygne lorde that now is, nor excepted in the said former acte in fourme abouesaid, other then suche as by the kings commissyons in fourme hereafter mēcioned shalbe altered, transposed, or chaunged, and all manours, landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, rentes, tithes, pencions, porcions, and other hereditamentes, and thinges aboue mencioned, belonging to them or any of them: and also al Manours, landes, tenementes, rentes, and other hereditamēts and thinges aboue mencyoned by any maner of assuraunce, conueygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, wil, deuise, or otherwise, had, made, suffered, knoweleged, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, geuen, assigned, limytted, or appoynted to the findinge of anye Priest, to haue continuaunce for euer, and wherewith, or whereby any priest was susteined, mainteined, or founde within fiue yeres nexte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the first day of this present parliament, whiche were not in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and real possession of the saide late kyng, nor in the actual and real possession of our soueraigne lorde the king that now is: and also, al an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual rents, profites, and emolumentes at any time within fiue yeares next before the begynning of this present Parliament, emploied, paied or bestowed, toward, or for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> maintenaunce, supportacion, or finding of any stipendarie prieste, intending by any acte, or wryting to haue cōti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce for euer, shall by the aucthoritie of this presente Parliament, immediatlye after the feast of Easter next comming, be adiudged &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and also be in the very actual and real possession and season of the
<pb facs="tcp:150873:28"/> king our souereigne lord, &amp; his heires, and successors for euer, without anye office or other inquisicion thereof to bee had, or founde, and in as large and ample maner and fourme, as the priestes, wardens, masters ministers, gouernours, rulers, or other incumbentes of them, or any of them, at any time within fiue yeres next before the beginninge of thys present Parliament, had, occupied or enioyed, or now hath, occupyeth, or enioyeth the same, and as though all and singuler the said Colleges free chappelles, chauntries, stipendes, salaries of priestes, and the saide manours, landes, tenementes, hereditamentes, and other the premis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses whatsoeuer they be, &amp; euery of them, were in this present acte spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, particulerly, and certeinlye rehearsed, named, and expressed by ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>presse woordes, names, surnames, corporacions, titles, and faculties, &amp; in their natures, kindes, and qualities.</p>
            <p>And ouer that be it ordeined and enacted by the aucthoritye of this present parliament, that where anye mannours, landes, tenementes, tithes, pencions, porcions, rentes, profites, or other hereditaments, by any maner of assuraunce, conueighaunce, wil, deuise, or other wise at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time heretofore had, made, suffred, knowledged, or declared, were geuen, assigned, or appointed, to, or for, the maintenaunce, sustentacion, or finding of one priest, or of diuers pryests for terme of certain yeres yet continuing, and that any priste hath been mainteined, susteyned, or found with the same, or with the reuenues, or profites thereof wythin fiue yeres last, past, that the king from the saide feast of Easter next cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, shall haue and enioy in euery behalfe, for, and during al such time to come, euery suche, and like thinges, tenementes, heredytamentes, profites, and emolumentes, as the priest, or priestes oughte, or shoulde haue had, for, or toward his, or their maintenaūce, sustenaunce, or fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; for no lenger, or further time, nor for any other profit, auaūtage or commoditie therof to be taken.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaies, and it is ordeined &amp; enacted by the aucthoritye of this present parliament, that when &amp; assone as the time assigned, for the maintenaunce, sustentacion, or finding of the prieste, or priestes shall be expired and runne: that then it shalbe lawfull to euery person &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones, to whome any Manours, landes, tenementes, tithes, porcions, pēcions, rents, and other hereditamētes, or any of them should haue be longed, or apperteined, if the saide former Act and this Acte had neuer bene had, or made, to enter into, take, perceiue, haue and enioy the same without any maner of liueri, <hi>ouster le maine,</hi> peticion, or other suit to be made to the Kinge, in like maner, fourme, and condicion, to all entents construccions, and purposes, as though the saide former Acte and this Acte had neuer bene had, or made, and as though the Kinge had neuer had any season or possession therof. Any thing in the sayde former Acte or in this Acte, to the contrary in any wyse notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And be it ordeined and enacted by thaucthoritie of this present par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:150873:28"/> that the king our souereigne lorde, his heires, and successours from the saide feast of Easter next comming, shall haue hod, perceiue, &amp; enioy for euer al landes, tenementes, rentes, and other hereditaments which by any maner of assuraunce, conueighaunce, willes, will, deuise, or otherwise at any time heretofore had, made, suffred, knowleged, or declared, were geuen, assigned, or appoynted to goe, or bee employed whollye to the fynding, or maintenaunce of any anniuersarye, or obite or other like thing, entente, or purpose, or of any lighte, or lampe, in any churche or chappell, to haue continuaunce for euer, whiche hath beene kepte, or mainteined within fiue yeres nexte before the said first day of this present parliament.</p>
            <p>And also that where but parte of the issues, or reuenues of any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, landes, tenements, rentes, or other hereditamentes hath by any of the waies, or meanes abouesaide bee geuen, assygned, or appoynted to be bestowed, or employed to the finding or maintenaunce of any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersarye, or obite or other like thinge, intente, or purpose, or of anye light, or lampe in any churche or chappel, and to haue continuaunce for euer: that then our soueraigne lord the king shall from the sayde feaste of Easter next comming for euer haue, perceiue, and enioy euerye such summes of money, that in any one yere within fiue yeres next before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first day of this present parliament, hath been expended and bestowed about the finding, or mayntenance of any suche anniuersary, or obyte, or other like thinge, intente, or purpose of any lighte, or lampe, to hym, his heires, and successours for euer, as a rente charge to bee paied yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the feastes of Sainct Michaell the Archangell, and the Annunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acyon of our Lady Saincte Mary the Virgin, by euen porcions in the kinges courte of the Augmentacions, and reuenues of his trowne, or in any other court, or courtes, as the king hereafter shall appoynt. And that it shalbe lawful to our saide Soueraigne lord the king, his heirs and successours for none paymente of anye suche summe or summes of money, to distreine in the saide manours, landes, and tenementes of the issues and reuenues, whereof the saide anniuersarye, or obyte, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like thing, or any such light or lāpe was founde, susteined, or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned. And that for lacke of sufficient distresse, in or vppon anye of the premisses, whereof any of the saide yerely rentes, or summes of money should be paied by the space of one moneth next after, that anye of the saide rentes should be paied, and be not paied within the sayd moneth that then it shalbe lawful to, &amp; for our soueraigne Lorde the kinge, hys heires, and successours by vertue of this present acte, to enter into, and to haue, and possesse, as much of the landes, tenementes, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, wherof the said rent, or rents should be leuied, or paied, as the rent or rentes that should be leuied, or paied out of the fame, dothe, or shall amount or come to in yerely value, and the same lands, tenements and hereditamentes to holde and kepe, and to haue our sayde Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne
<pb facs="tcp:150873:29"/> lord the king, his heires and assignes for euer, or for suche estate as our soueraigne Lord the king, his heirs, or successors, had, or ought to haue had, of, or in the said rent, or rents.</p>
            <p>And it is also ordeined and enacted by the aucthoritie of this present Parliamente, that oure soueraigne lorde the kinge, shall from the saide feast of Easter next comming, haue, perceiue, and enioy al and singuler suche summes of moneye, profites, commodyties, and emolumentes, which by vertue of any maner of assuraunce, conueighaunce, cōposicy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will, deuife, or otherwise, heretofore haue ben geuen, assigned, limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or appointed to haue continuance for euer, whiche in any one yeare within fiue yeres next before the beginning of this present parlyament haue bene paied, bestowed, or emploied, by any maner of corporacions, guildes, fraternities, companies, or felowships of mysteryes, or crafts, or any of them, beinge in Englande, Wales, and other the Kyngs do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, or by the masters, wardeines, gouernours, or other officers, or ministers, or by the master, warden, gouernor, or other officer, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyster of them, or any of them, towarde, or about the finding, mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, or sustentacion of any prieste, or priestes, of anye annyuersary, or obit, lampe, light or lights, or other like thing, as is aforesaid, to our saide souereigne Lorde the king, his heires, and successoures for euer: to be paied yerely, as a rent charge, at the feastes of Sainct Michaell the Archaungel, and the Annunciation of our Lady, by euen porcions, in the kyngs court of Augmentacions, and reuenues of his crowne or in any other courte, or courts, as the kyng hereafter shall appoynt. And that it shalbe lawfull to oure saide soueraigne lord the king, his heires and successours for none paymente of anye suche summes, or summe of money, profite, commoditie, or emolumente, or for none payment of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of them, to distreigne in al y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> manors, lands, and tenements of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry suche craftes, corporacions, guildes, fraternityes, companyes, or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowshippes of misteryes or craftes, or any, of them, by whom, or by the masters, wardens, gouernors, or other officers, or ministers, or master wardē, gouernour, or minister, of the whiche any suche sūmes, or sūme of money, profite, commoditie, or emolument, haue or hath been payed bestowed, or employed: And that all and euery of the saide summes of money, profites, commodities, and emolumentes, shal from the feast of Easter next comming, without any maner of inquisicion, or office to be had, or founde, be iudged and demed to be in the actual and real posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of our said Soueraigne Lord the king, in like maner &amp; fourme, to all intentes, construction, &amp; purposes, as if the same had ben particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and specially mencioned in this present acte.</p>
            <p>And furthermore be it ordeined &amp; enacted by aucthoritie aforesayde that the kyng our souereigne Lorde,, shall from the saide feaste of Eas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter next comming, haue, and enioye to him, his heires, and successours for euer, all fraternities, brotherheddes, and guildes, being within the
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:150873:29"/> Realme of England, and Wales, and other the kings dominions: and al manours, landes, tenementes, and other hereditaments, belonging to them, or any of them other then such corporacions, guildes, fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, companies, and felowshippes of misteries, or crafts, &amp; the manors landes, tenementes, and other heredytamentes, perteining to the said corporacions, guildes, fraternities, companies, and felowships of mys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teryes, or craftes aboue mencyoned: and shall by vertue of this acte be iudged and demed, in actuall and real possessyon of our said soueraign Lorde the king his heires, and successours, from the said feast of Eas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter next comming for euer, without any inquisicions or office therof to be had or found.</p>
            <p>And also be it ordeined and enacted by the aucthority aforesaid, that our said souereigne lord the king, hys heires and successours, at his &amp; their will and pleasure may direct his, and theire commissions and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myssyon vnder the greate Seale of Englande to suche persones as it shal please him. And that the same commissioners, or twoe of them at the least, shall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of this acte, &amp; of the said commissyon, as well to Surueye all and synguler laye cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poracyons, guyldes, fraternytyes, companyes, and felowshyppes of mysteries, or craftes incorporate, and euerye of them, as all other the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide fraternyties, brotherheddes, and guyldes wythin the lymyttes of theire commission, to them directed: And all the Guydences, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posicions, bookes of accomptes, and other wrytinges of euery of thē, to the intente thereby to knowe, what money, and other thyngs was payed, or bestowed to the fyndinge, or maintenaunce of anye pryeste, or pryestes anniuersarye, or obite, or other lyke thynge, lyght, or lāpe, by them, or anye of them: as also to inquire, search, and trie by al suche wayes and meanes, as to them shall bee thoughte meete and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, what manoures, landes, tenementes, rentes, and other heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, profytes, commodytyes, emolumentes, and other thynges be geeuen, lymitted, or appointed to our saide soueraigne lorde the kyng by thys acte wythin the lymittes of theire commyssyon. And also that the same commyssioners or two of them at the least, by vertue of thys acte, and of the commissyon to them directed, shal haue full power and aucthoritie to assigne, and shall appointe in euerye suche place wheare guylde, fraternitye the pryeste, or incumbent of any Chauntrye in <hi>esse,</hi> the first daye of thys presente Parlyamente by the foundacyon ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, the firste institucion thereof, shoulde or ought to haue kepte a Grammer Schole, or a preacher, and so hathe doone: sithen the feaste of Sainct Mychael the Archaungell laste paste, landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes of euerye suche Chauntrye, guylde, and fraternitye to remaine, and continue in successyon to a Schole Mays<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or preacher for euer, for, and towarde the kepynge of a Grammer Schole, or Preachinge, and for suche Godlye ententes, and purposes,
<pb facs="tcp:150873:30"/> and in such maner and fourme, as the same Commissioners, or twoe of them at the least shal assigne, or appointe: And also to make and ordein a Vicare to haue perpetuitie for euer, in euerye Paryshe churche the first day of this present Parlyamente, beinge a college, free chappel, or chauntrie, or appropried, annexed, or vnited to anye colledge, free chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; or chauntrie, that shall come to the kynges hands by vertue of this acte, and to endowe euery suche Vicare sufficientlye, hauing respect to his cure and charge, the same endowement to be to euery suche Vicar, and to his successours for euer, without any other licence, or graunte of the kynge, the Bishoppe, or other Officers of the Diocese. And also the saide commissioners, or two of them at the least, shall haue aucthoritye by force of this acte, to assigne in euerye greate Towne, or Parishe, where they shal thinke necessarye to haue moe Priests then one for the ministring of the Sacramentes, within the same Towne, or paryshe, Landes, and tenementes belonginge to any chauntrye, chappelle, or stipendary Priest being within the same towne, or parishe the first day of this present Parliament, to bee to suche persone and persones, as the saide commissioners, or twoe of them at the leaste, shall assygne, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point to continue in succession for euer, for, and towardes the suffycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent finding, and maintenance of one, or moe Priestes wythin the same towne or paryshe, as by the saide commissioners, or twoe of them shall bee thought necessarie, or conuenient. And aswel to make ordinaunces and rules, concerning the seruice, vse, and demeanour of euerye suche Priest and Scholemasters, as is aforesaid, to be appointed, as also by what name, or names, he and they shall from henceforth be named and called. And also that the saide commissioners, or twoe of them at the least, shall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of this act, and of the saide commissyon to them directed to assigne aswel to euery deane, Master, warden, prouost, and other Incumbente, and minister of any of the saide colledges, free chappelles, or chauntryes, beynge wythin the limittes of theire commission, whiche hereafter shal be dissolued, or determined by vertue of this acte. as to euerye Stypendarye Priest, and other Priest, whose Salary the king shalbe intituled vnto by this acte, as to euery felow and poore persone, hauing yearely reliefe out of any of the saide colleges, free chappelles, or chauntryes beinge within the limittes of theire commission. suche seueral yerely annuities, pency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or other recompenses, during their seueral liues, as to the same cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, or two of them shall bee thoughte meete and conuenyente. And ouer that the saide commissioners, or twoe of them at the least, shall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of this acte, and of the commissyon to them directed, to inquire, and trye by suche waies and meanes as they shall thinke meete and conuenient, what moneye, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte and benefyte any poore persone, or persones by vertue of anye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighance, assuraunce, composicion, wil deuise, or otherwise, heretofore
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:150873:30"/> had or made, intended or meant to haue continuance for euer, had, or enioyed, wythin fiue yeres, next before the beginning of thys presente parliament out of any college, free chappelle, or chauntry, &amp; other y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses geuen; limitted, or appointed to the king by this act, being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limittes of their commission. And therupon to make assignemēts and orders in suche maner and fourme, as al and synguler suche fayde money, profite and commoditie shal bee paied to poore people for euer: Accordyng to suche saide assurance, composicyon, wyl, deuise, or other thyng had; or made, for the same, and to assigne and appoint, lands, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes or other hereditaments, parcel of the premisses for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce and continuaunce of the same for euer, and also to appoint to fraternityes, brotherheddes, and guildes, landes, tenementes, &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dytamentes parcell of the premisses towardes and for the mayntenāce of piers, iutties, walles, or bankes, against the rages of the sea, hauens and creekes. And that all and singuler annuityes, pencions, and other recompences, shalbe halfe yerely payed to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> persons, to whom the same ought to be payed by the kynges Receyuour for the time being, of hys landes commonly called the suppressed lands, or other his reuenues, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the countie or citye, where such colledge, free chappel, or chaūtry or other the premisses geuen, limitted or appointed to the king, by thys act, the first day of this present parliament, were or remained without any fee, or rewarde therfore to be paied: The first payment to begin at the feaste of saint Michaell the Archaungell nexte comming. And that euery suche receiuour, vpon his accompt, shall haue full and due allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of all suche annuities, pencions; &amp; other recompences by him pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by vertue of any such assignement to be made, by the said commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners or two of them at the least.</p>
            <p>And it is ordeyned and enacted by the aucthority of this present par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that the said commissioners, and euery of them, that shall take vpon him y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> execuciō of any of the said commissions, shalbe bound, as he wil answer before God, to execute the cōmissiō, to him &amp; other directed beneficially towards the deanes, maisters, wardens, prouosts, &amp; other incumbents, and ministers aforesaide, and towardes the poore people, concerning the said assygnements, and also toward the maintenance of piers, iutties, walles, or bankes, againste the rages of the sea, hauens &amp; creekes: And that al maner of assignements &amp; ordinaunces to be made by the said commissioners, or two of thē at the least and certified vnder their seales or the seales of two of thē at the least, into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kinges courte of the augmentacyons &amp; reuenues of his crowne, or to any other court or courtes, by the kinges maiesty to be made or assigned, shal by vertue of this acte, and of the saide commissioners, bee as good and effectuall in the law to al intēts, cōstructions and purposes, as thoughe the same had ben assigned and ordeined by aucthoritie of this present parliamēt by expresse and apte wordes, termes, and sentences.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150873:31"/>
            <p>Prouided also, that such annuities, pencions, or other recompences, that the saide commissioners, or any of them, shall assigne or appoynt to be paide yerely to any such deane master, warden, gouernour: or other incumbent, felow, or minister, shall not extend to any more clere yerely value, then suche deane, master, warden, prouost, gouernor or other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent, felow, or minister, or his predecessor lawfully had, or enioyed in money, meate, drink, liuerie, or allowance of the same yerely, within fiue yeres, next before the beginning of this present parliament,</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that if any of the said maisters, wardēs, prouosts, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors, or other incumbēts, felow, or ministers, shal at any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, during his life, be promoted by the king to any benefice, or other spiritual promocion, being of a better clere yerely value then hys sayde annuitie or pencion, or other recōpence shalbe of: that then thannuitie, penciō, or other recōpence, that any such deane, master, warden, gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, prouost, or other incūbent, felow, minister, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> so shalbe {pro}moted shal haue, shal īmediatly after such {pro}mociō had, cease, &amp; vtterly determine.</p>
            <p>And be it ordeined &amp; enacted by thaucthoritie of this presesent parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that the said commissioners, or two of them at the least, to whō any cōmission by vertue or meane of this act, shalbe directed &amp; delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red shalbe bounden vpon the forfaiture, of euery of them of a hundreth pound, to make certificat vnder their seales, or the seales of two of thē at the least into the saide court of the augmentacions, and reuenues of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kings crowne, or into any other court, as is aforesaid, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>in one yeare next after the commission to them directed, of al manours, lands, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, tents, tithes, porcions, pencions, heredytaments, &amp; recompēces by the same commissioners or two of them, assigned or appointed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the vses, intents, or purposes aboue mencioned.</p>
            <p>And also be it ordeined &amp; enacted, by thaucthority of this presēt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that our souereigne lorde the king shall haue &amp; enioy all suche goods, cattels, iuels, plate, ornaments, &amp; other moueables, as were or be the common goods of euery such college, chauntrye, freechappell, or stipendarie prist, belonginge or annexed to the furniture or seruices of their seueral foundations, or abused of any of the saide corporaciōs, in the abuses aforesaid, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> propertie wherof was not altered nor chaūged before the .viii. day of December in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yere of our lord god M.D.xlvii.</p>
            <p>And it is also ordeined &amp; enacted by thaucthoritie of this presēt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that al suche debtes and sūmes of money, as ought, or shoulde without fraude or couin hereafter be paied of the moneye or goods of any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said colleges, due, or paiable, by reason of any cōtract, specialty or promise, had or made, before the same .viii. day, shal truely &amp; fully be paied by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> treasorer of the kings court of thaugmentaciōs &amp; reuenues of his crown, or by the tresorer or receiuer of any other court, to which any of the premisses shalbe appointed of the kinges treasure, beinge in his or their handes, with as conueniēt spede, as the same may be paid</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:150873:31"/>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it ordeyned and enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, thac this acte, or any article, clause, or matter conteyned in the same, shal not in any wise extēde to any College, Hostoll, or Halle, being within eyther of the vniuersities of Cambrige and Oxforde, nor to any Chauntrie founded in any of the Colleges, Hostelles, or Halles, beinge in the same Vniuersities, nor to the free chappell of Sainct George, the Martire, situate in the Castle of Windesore, nor to the College, called sainct Mary College of Winchester, besides Winchester, of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Bishoppe Wikham, nor to the College of Eton, nor to the parish churche, commonly called the Chapel in the sea in Newton, within the Isle of Ely, in the countie of Cambrige, nor to anye Manours, landes, tenementes or hereditamentes, to them, or to anye of them pertaining, or belonging, nor to anye Chappel made or ordeined, for the ease of the people, dwelling distaunt from the parish churche, or suche like chappel, whereunto no more landes or tenementes, then the churchyarde, or a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle house or close, doth belong or perteine, nor to any cathedral church or College, where a Bishoppes sea is within thys realme of Englande, or in Wales, nor to the Manoures, landes, tenementes, or other heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of any of them, other then to such Chauntries, Obites, Lightes and Lampes, or any of them, as at any tyme within fiue yeres next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the begynning of thys present parlament, haue been hadde, vsed, or maintened, within the saide cathedrall churches, or within any of them, or the issues, reuenues, or profites of any of the said cathedral Churchs, to whiche Chauntries, Obites, lightes and lampes, it is enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that thys acte shall extende.</p>
            <p>And it is ordeyned &amp; enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that oure soueraigne lord the kyng at any tyme, during hys lyfe (whiche God lōg preserue, maye at hys will and pleasure, alter and chaunge the name or names, of all and singular Chauntries, and the Foundations of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, being in any of the Colleges, Hostelles, or halles, of any of the sayde Vniuersities, according as to hys godly, wisedome shalbe thought mete and conuenient.</p>
            <p>Sauing to all and euery persone and persons, bodies politike and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, theire heires and successours, and the heires and successoures of euerye of them, other then the Maisters, wardens, Ministers, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures, Rulers, Priestes, Incumbentes, Felowes, and brethren of the saide Colleges, Chauntries, freechappels, and other the premisses, geuē limitted, or appointed to the kyng by thys acte: &amp; the successours of thē, and euery of them, and other then such as bee, or pretende to bee, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doures, patrones, or donours of the premisses, or any of them, or of anye part or parcell therof, and the heires, successours and assignes of euery, or any of them: and other then such as bee, or were feoffees, recoueries, conisies, grauntees, or deuisees of any of the premisses, to, or for any of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vses, purposes, or ententes aboue mentioned, or to the vse of anye of the
<pb facs="tcp:150873:32"/> sayd Colleges, Free chappels, chauntries, or other the premisses, geuen, limitted, or appointed by thys act to the kyng, or to the entēt to employe the rentes or profites thereof, to the vse of Maisters, Rulers, Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentes, or Ministers of them, or any of them: and other then suche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone and persones, and bodies politike and corporate, theire heires, suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours, and assignes, as claime or pretende, to haue estate, right, title, interest, vse, possession, or condition, of, in, or to the premisses, or any part or parcel thereof, by reason of anye feoffement, fine, bargain and sale, or by any other wayes, meanes, or conueighaunce to them made, of any estate of enheritaunce, without the saide late kynges licence, assent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, or agreement, and without the licence, assent, or agrement, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Maiestie that nowe is, by any of the saide Deanes, maisters, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deines, ministers, gouernours, rulers, priests, or incumbentes, or by the Foundours, donours, or patrones of them, or of anye of them, all suche righte, title, clayme, possession, interest, rentes, annuities, commodities, commons, offices, fees, leases, liueries, liuinges, pencions, portions, deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, dueties, and other profites, which they, or any of thē lawfully haue, or of right ought to haue, or might haue had, in, of, or to anye of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses, or in, of, or to any part or parcel therof, in such like maner, fourme and condition, to all ententes, respectes, constructions, and purposes, as if this act had neuer been had nor made, and as though the said Chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tries, colleges, and other the sayde promotions, had still continued and remained in their full being: and sauing to all and euerye Patrone, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, foundour, or gouernour of any such college, Chauntrie, free chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, Stipendary priestes, and other the premisses, geuen, limitted, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the kyng by thys act, and the donour, feoffoure, and geuer of the aforesaide landes, tenementes, or hereditamentes, to them, or anye of them, or to anye vses, or purposes before mentioned, all suche rentes, seruices, rentes secke, rentes charge, fees, annuities, profits, and offices: and also lease for terme of life, lyues, and yeres, whereupon the accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med rent, or more, is reserued, as they, or any of them lawfully had, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and enioyed, in, out, or of any the sayd promotions, or out of any of the sayde landes, tenementes, or hereditamentes, before the first day of thys present parlament.</p>
            <p>And ouer that, it is ordeined and enacted by the aucthoritie of thys present parlament, that all and euery persone and persons, beinge in life, which haue, or hath for any sōme of money to him or thē, payed, bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or solde, any Manours, landes, tenementes, or other hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes aforesaide, whereunto the kyng our souereigne lord is intituled, by vertue of thys acte, shall repaye to suche persone, as so bought any of the sayde Manoures, Landes, Tenementes, or other Hereditamentes, or to hys Executours or assignes, vpon a request therfore made, or within three Monethes, then nexte ensuing the same requeste, as much money, as he, or they receiued, for the sale of any thing, so by hym or them solde,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150873:32"/> And for none payment therof, such persone and persones as purchased, or bought the sayde landes, tenementes, and other the premisses, or any parcell therof, and their executours and administratours, shalbee enha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled by thauctoritie of thys present parlament, to sue, and maintain an action of debt at the common lawes of thys realme, against such person or persones, as so bargained or solde to hym or thē, or to their testatour anye of the premisses, belonging to any college, chauntrie, free chapel, or other promotion spirituall, in which action of debte, none essoine, protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or wager of lawe shalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>And bee it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that all, and euery of the saide chauntries, colleges, &amp; freechapels, and other the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses, geuen, limitted, or appointed to the kyng by thys acre, and all the mansion houses, manours, landes, tenementes, possessions, and heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes, and other the premisses whatsoeuer they be, geuen, limitted, &amp; appointed to the kyng by thys acte, and euery parte and parcell of thē whiche by aucthoritie and vertue of thys acte, been vested, adiudged, &amp; demed, or shalbe in the kynges maiesties possession &amp; handes, or whiche the kyng shalbe entitled vnto, by vertue of thys acte, shalbe in the order, suruaye and gouernaunce of our souerein lord the kynges courte of the Augmentations and reuenues of his crowne, or in suche other court as the kyng at anye time hereafter shall assigne, name, or appoincte, and so shall, and may be graunted, letten, and sette to the farme by the Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, officers, and ministres of the same courte, or of any other courte so to bee appointed, in suche maner and fourme, as other manoures, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, tenementes, appointed to the same courte of Augmentations, and reuenues of hys graces Crowne, or other court so to be appointed, ben to bee graunted or letten: And that all the farmes, issues, reuenues and profites, comming &amp; growing of the same premisses, and of euerye parte thereof, shalbe taken and receiued to the kynges vse, by the officers and ministers of the same court or courtes, in such maner and fourme, as is vsed and had of other manours, landes, and tenements, &amp; of the issues, reuenues, and profits of the same, committed to the order, rule, suruay, and gouernance of the sayd court of the Augmentations and reuenues of the kyngs crowne, or any other court so to bee appointed: any act, sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, ordinaunce, custome, or vse, heretofore had, made, or vsed, to the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by aucthoritie aforesayde, that if any of the saide Maisters, Wardeins, Ministers, Rulers, Gouernours, Priestes, Incumbentes, or owners of any suche college, chauntrie, free chappell, or of any the premisses, geuen, limitted, or appointed to the kyng by this acte, or of any of them, sithens the xxiii. day of Nouembre, in the xxxvii. yere of the reigne of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said late kyng, haue made any lease, vnder hys or theire common Seale, or otherwise, for terme of yeres, lyfe, or lyues, of theire sayde colleges, chauntries, freechapels, or of other the same pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses,
<pb facs="tcp:150873:33"/> or of any part thereof, or of any Manours, Landes, Tenements, possessions, or hereditamentes, whatsoeuer they be, to them, or to any of them, vnited, or annexed, belonging, or appertaininge, vpon the whiche leasses, the vsual and olde rentes and fermes, accustomed to bee yelden and reserued, or more, by the space of xx. yeres next before the saide xxiii. daye of Nouembre, not reserued and yelden, shalbe vtterly voide and of none effecte: and that all other leasses and grauntes, heretofore made of any the premisses, geuen, limitted, or appointed to the kynge by thys acte, shalbe as good, auaileable, and effectual in the law, to all intentes, constructions, and purposes, as if this act had neuer been had, or made, any thing in this act, or any other act hertofore had or made, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereof, in anye wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; be it further ordeined &amp; enacted by the auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforesayd, that thys acte, or any thing therein conteined, shall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to anye manours, lands, tenementes, possessions, or hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whiche the saide Maistres, wardeins, Ministres, Chauntrie prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, Incumbentes, or other the sayde Gouernours, Officers, ministers, or rulers of the premisses, or of anye of them, hath, or is, or hereafter shal haue, or bee possessed, or seased of in fee simple, fee taile general or special for terme of lyfe, terme of yeres, or otherwise, to hys or theire owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre vses, by enheritaunce, or purchase: and not beinge at anye time vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or annexed, to hys or theire saide Colleges, Free chappels, Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, or other the premisses, geuen, limitted, or appointed to the kynge by thys acte: nor shall extende to anye Manoures, landes, tenementes, possessions, rentes, annuities, and yerelye pencion, or pencions, or to any yerelye summe, or summes of money, being not vnited, or parcell of any the sayde Colleges, and other the premisses aforesayde, or of anye of thē heretofore geuen or graunted by the saide late kyng, or geuen or graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or herafter to be geuen or graūted by the kyng our souereigne lord, to any of the said Deanes, Maisters, wardeins, Ministers, Chauntrie priestes, Incumbentes, gouernours, or rulers of the premisses, or of any of them, for terme of lyfe onely, vnder hys greate Seale of England, or vnder the Seale of the Courte of the Augmentations, and reuenues of the kynges crowne, or any other of the kynges seales, of any of hys cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes: any thing conteined in thys act, to the cōtrary in any wise notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, and bee it enacted by aucthoritie aforesayde, that as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel, all and euery patrone, Donour, Foundour, and geuer of any of the saide promotions, or premisses, or geuer, donour, or Feoffer, of any their Landes, Tenementes, Possessions, or other hereditamentes, as all and euerye persone and persones, bodies politike and corporate, whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the making of thys Acte, lawfullye without fraude or couine, had, or enioyed, any maner of rent, or other yerely profites, to bee taken, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, or had, of any Chauntries, colleges, free chappelles, or other the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150873:33"/> premisses, geuen, limitted, or appointed to the kyng by thys acte, or oute of anye Manours, Landes, Tenementes, or other possessions of them, or any of them shall haue and enioy the same, in like maner and fourme, as they should and ought to haue doen, if the saide colleges, chauntries, free chappelles, and other the premisses geuen, limitted, or appointed to the kynge by thys acte, had still remained and continued in esse, and full being: any thing in thys act mentioned to the contrary in anye wise not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and bee it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that yf anye suche gouernour, ruler, wardein, maister, incumbent, minister, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hauing any of the said spiritual promotions, or incumbentes, haue, or shal compounde for the first fruites of any such spiritual promotions, accordinge to the lawes and statutes of thys Realme, and the dayes of payment of any part therof, not expired before the first day of thys par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, that all summes of money so to bee due and payable sithens the sayd first daye of thys parlament, shall ceasse, and bee not payd, asked, or demaūded: any bonde, recognisaunce, suertie, or other thing had, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided always, &amp; be it enacted by the auctoritie aforesayd, that all suche rentes, seruices, issues, profites, and other summes of money paya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble out, of, or for any of the premisses, or any of thē, in the kyngs courte of hys Excheker, shall continue, and be continually and yerelye leuied, charged, or paied in the same courte, in suche maner and fourme, as her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore hath ben vsed: any lawe, custome, vnitie of possession in the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hyghnesse, or other thing to the contrary notwithstanding: And as though the said promotions, Manours, landes, tenementes, and other the premisses had not come to the kyngs handes or possession.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayde, that all and euery letters patentes made by the said late king Henry the eight, or by the kyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> maiestie that now is, or herafter to be made by hys hyghnes, to any persone or persones, or to any archbishoppe, or bishoppe, of any of the saide colleges, chauntries, free chappelles, or other the premisses, or any part or parcel of them, or of any landes, tenements or hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, belonging or appertaining, or that did belong, or apperteine to thē, or to anye of them: And all fines, giftes, grauntes, feoffements, recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and all other assurances and conueighaunces therof had or made, by the assent, consent, or licence, vnder the great Seale of Englande, of the sayde late kynge Henrye the eighte, or of the kynges Maiestie that now is, to anye persone or persones, bodies politike or corporate, by any Chauntrie priest, Maister, wardein, minister, ruler, gouernour, or other hauinge anye of the sayde promotions, of anye of the sayde Colleges, chauntries, free chappels, or other the premisses, or of any of them, or of any part, parcell, or membre of the same, shall stande and bee in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and effectes, and shalbee good and effectual in the lawe, for suche
<pb facs="tcp:150873:34"/> estatutes and interestes, geuen, graunted, limitted, or appointed in any of the gyftes, grauntes, assurances, or conueighances therof had or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, according to their purportes, fourme &amp; maner, and according to the true entent and meaning of the same assurances, and shalbee by auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of thys acte, good, parfite, and auaileable, aswel against the kynge, hys heires and successours, as against the saide chauntrie priestes, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deins, maisters, rulers, gouernours, and other hauing any of the sayde promotions, and their successours, and the successours of euery of them: as also against the foundours, donours, and patrones of the same, &amp; the ordinary of them, and euery of them, and the heires and successoures of euery of them: any lawe, statute, ordinaunce, or other thing, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereof notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And where diuers and sundrye Bishoppes, Deanes, Archedeacones, Treasaurours, Prebendaries, Chauntrie priestes, maisters, prouostes, Rulers, Gouernours of anye Deaneries, Archedeaneries, Treasauror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippes, Prebendes, freechappels, Chauntries, or Colleges, within this realme of England, and other the kyngs Maiesties dominions, or any of the patrones, foundours, donours of any of the Bishoprickes, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saurourshippes, Deaneries, Chauntries, free chappels, or other the said Spiritual promotions, of their voluntary willes or mindes, for diuers good and reasonable causes and considerations, by deede or deedes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled, or by other writinges, or conueighaunces heretofore geuen and graunted to the late king of famous memory Henry the eight, late king of Englād, &amp; to hys heyrs, or to our souereigne lord the kyng that now is, and to hys heires, diuers of their Deaneries, Archedeaneries, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saurorshippes, Prebendes, Chappelles, Chauntries, &amp; colleges, or anye other ecclesiasticall or spirituall promotions last before remembred and all, or some part of the Manoures, landes, tenementes, tithes, pencions, annuities, rentes, reuertions, and other reuenues, hereditamentes, pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions, emolumentes and profites, to the same Bishoprickes, deaneries, colleges, and other like promotions, benefices, offices, &amp; dignities, or to any of them belonging, apperteining, vnited, or annexed, or whiche the saide bishoppes, deanes, archedeacons, treasaurors, chauntrie priestes, maisters, prouostes, rulers, gouernours, and other Ecclesiasticall, or spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual officers or ministers, or any of the said patrones, donours, or foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dours, or any of them had, or enioyed in the right, or by reason of any of the same promotions, offices, or dignities.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that all and euery gyftes, and grauntes heretofore made to the said late kyng, and to hys heires, or to our souereigne lord the kyng that now is, and to hys heirs, by any Archebishoppe, Bishoppe, Deane, Archedeacon, Treasaurour, Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary, Maister, Prouost, gouernoure, or other the saide Ecclesiasticall or spiritual persone or persons, or by any patrones, donour, or foundour of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150873:34"/> any of the said Deaneries, Chauntries, or other of the sayd spiritual, or Ecclesiastical promotions, or of all, or any of the manours, landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, tithes, rentes, reuersions, pencions, portiōs, annuities, or other hereditamentes, reuenues, emolumentes, profites, or commodities, to any of the said benefices, offices, prebendes, promotions, or dignities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, apperteining, vnited, or annexed, or whiche any of the same ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chebishoppes, Bishoppes, Deanes, Archedeacons, Treasaurours, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Prouostes, Prebendaries, Rulers, Gouernours, Officers, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, Patrones, Foundours, or Donours, had, or enioyed, or haue, or enioye, or ought to haue or enioye, in the righte, or by reason, or meanes of any of the same promotions, offices, or dignities, shalbe good &amp; effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall in the lawe, to all intentes and purposes: Sauing to all and euery persone and persones, and bodies politike and corporate, theire heires, successours, and assignes, and to the heires, successours, and assignes of euery of them, other then the Archebishops, Bishops, Deanes, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, treasaurours, prebendaries, rulers, gouernoures, wardeines, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uostes, geuours, and grauntours of any of the premisses, &amp; their heires, successours, and assignes, and other then suche ecclesiasticall, or spirituall persones, bodies politike or corporate, as are, or pretende to bee foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, donours, patrons, or ordinaries of the premisses, or any of them, all such rightes, titles, interestes, claimes, entrees, rentes, reuersions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders, fees, offices, annuities, landes, tenementes, hereditamentes, profites, commodities, and emolumentes, as they or any of them haue, or should, or ought to haue had, of, in, or to the premisses next aboue mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, or any part therof, as if this act had neuer ben had, or made, any thing in thys act to the contrary in anye wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that thys acte, or any thing therin conteined, shall not in any wise extende to make good or effectuall, any gyft, graunt, bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gain, sale, or alienation made by anye person, or Vicare of theire Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, or Vicarages, or of any part or parcell thereof, or of any thing to them, or any of them belonging or apperteining.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, that thys acte, or any thing therein conteined, shall not in any wise extende, to hinder or preiudice George Brooke knight, lord Cobhā, his heires, or assignes, for, or cōcerninge the late college of Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, in the Countie of Kente, or the Manours, landes, tenementes, or possessions therof: any thing aboue mentioned to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> contrary, in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted, by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that this present acte, or any thing therein conteined, shall in any wise extende, or be preiudicial or hurtful to the general corporatiō of any citie, borough, or Towne, within thys realme, or anye other the kynges dominiōs, ne shall extende to anye the landes, or hereditamentes, of them, or anye of them: Any thing herein conteined, to the contrary in any wise notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150873:35"/>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that all suche of the saide colleges, free chappels, chauntries, and other the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses, being appointed and geuen to the kyngs hyghnesse, by the aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie of thys act, as be within the Duchie of Lancaster, &amp; all manoures, Landes, Tenementes, and hereditamentes, perteining or belonging to the same colleges, free chappels, and chauntries, shall after the said feast of Easter nexte comming, be within the surueye &amp; order of the courte of the Duchie of Lancastre, in suche maner and fourme, as other the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses bee assigned or appointed by aucthoritie of thys acte, to be in the surueye and order of the Court of the Augmentations and reuenues of the kynges crowne, or other court by the kyng to be assigned: and that all commissions, that hereafter shalbe awarded by vertue &amp; force of this acte, concerning suche colleges, free chappels, chauntries, and other the premisses, as bee within the said Duchie of Lancastre, shalbe awarded vnder the great seale of England, &amp; shalbe certified into the same courte of the Duchie of Lancastre: any thing abouesaid to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; bee it enacted by the auctoritie aforesayde, that this acte, ne any thing therein conteined, shall extende to the College, or chauntrie of Attylbourghe in the countie of Norffolke, which the sayde late king Henry the eight gaue to Robart, late Earle of Sussex, &amp; to his heirs: but that Henry now Earle of Sussex, sonne and heire to the said late Erle, hys heires and assignes, shall, &amp; maye, by thauctoritie of thys acte, haue and enioy the sayde college, and chauntrie, and all Manours, Landes, Tenementes, aduowsons, tithes, pencions, portions, and other hereditaments thereunto belonging or appertaining: any thing in this acte, to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided always, and by the auctoritie aforesaide, bee it enacted, that the kynges Maiestie, at any tyme, when it shal seeme to hym good, may geue auctoritie to certain hys graces commissioners, to alter the nature and condition of all maner of Obites, aswell within the vniuersities of Cambridge and Oxforde, as in any other place, within thys hys graces realme of Englande and Wales, being not suppressed ne annichilate by vertue of thys present acte, and the same Obites so altered, to dispose to a better vse, as to the reliefe of some poore men being studētes, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise.</p>
            <p>Prouided also, and be it enacted by aucthoritie aforesaide, that it shal not be lefull to any persone or persones, bodies politike or corporate, by reason of anye remainder, vse, or condition, to enter into, clayme, or chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge any landes, tenementes, or hereditamentes, for the none doynge, not naming, or none finding of anye suche priest or priestes, or poore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, as is aforesaide, obite, anniuersary, light or lampe, from henceforth to be founden or doen: any thing herein conteined, to the cōtrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:150873:35"/>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that thys act, nor any thing therein cōteined, shal in any wise extende to any landes, tenementes, possessions, or heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes whatsoeuer, that any maister, Deane, Prebendary, wardein, or chauntrie, or any Stipendary priest of any college, chauntrie, prebende, fraternitie, guylde, or any other corporations haue, or helde of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone or persones, by copie of courte rolle, or at will, according to the cus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of any manour or manours: nor geue or graunt any copyhold lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to the kynges hyghnesse.</p>
            <p>And also prouided, that the kynges highnes, his heires, or successours, shall not in any wise haue, holde, enioy, or take by vertue of thys acte, or any article therin conteined, any maner of copyhold, landes, tenements, possessions, or hereditamentes whatsoeuer they be: but that all &amp; euery of the saide persones and incumbentes shall haue, holde, and enioye the same, during their liues, towardes their pencion and yerely liuing, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rentes, and doing their customes and seruices thereof due &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed: any thing in thys acte, to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided, that thys act shall not extende to any landes, tenementes, or hereditamentes assigned, appointed, or intended for the findinge, or maintenaunce of anye chauntrie priest, or stipendary priest, whiche by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny former right, and good title, without fraude or couine, were lawfully recouered from the possession of any such chauntrie priest, or stipendarie priest, before the first day of Octobre: the saide xxxvii. yere of the reigne of the said late kyng Henry the eight, whiche landes, tenementes, &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditamentes were not charged, nor chargeable to the paiment of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual tenthe: any thing in thys act, to the contrary hereof notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaid, that all and singular grauntes, licences, confirmations, &amp; letters Patentes, whiche our late souereigne lord kyng Henry the eight, or our souereign lord the kyng that now is, haue made vnder the great seale of England to any persone or persones, bodies politike or corporate, of anye college, chappel, or chauntrie nowe being in esse, or standing, or now not beinge in esse, or not standing, or of any lordshippes, manours, landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and hereditamentes, annexed, vnited, belonging, or apperteining to any college, chappell, or chauntrie now being in esse, or standing, or now not being in esse, or not standing, or of anye other thing or thinges men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, expressed, or conteined in any such graunt, licence, confirmation, or letters patentes, shall from henceforth bee demed, taken, expouned, &amp; adiudged good and effectual in the lawe, according to the wordes, sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, meaninges, ententes, fourme, and effectes of the same grauntes, licences, confirmations, and letters patentes, to all intentes, constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and purposes, as if thys acte, and the sayde acte made in the sayde xxxvii. yere of the said late kyng Henry the eight, had neuer ben had, nor
<pb facs="tcp:150873:36"/> made. And that thys act, or the said act made in the sayde xxxvii. yere of the reigne of our said late souereigne lord kyng Henry the eight, or any clause, article, sentence, or other thing therein conteined, shal not extend to any Colleges, Chappels, Chauntries, or other thing or thinges men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this act, now being in esse, or stāding, or now not being in esse, or not standing, or to any manours, lands, tenementes, possessions, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, or hereditaments, annexed, vnited, belonging, or apperteininge to any College, Chappell, Chauntrie, or other thing mentioned in this act now being in esse or standing, or now not being in esse, or not standing, or to anye other thing or thinges, mentioned, or expressed in thys Acte: whiche any persone or persones, bodies politike or corporate haue had, or obteined, by the assent, licence, cōfirmation, graunt, or letters Paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the said late kyng, or of the kyngs Maiestie that now is: nor shall extende to any Manours, Landes, Tenementes, Reuenues, possessiōs, hereditamentes, or other thing or thinges, mentioned, expressed, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in any such licence, confirmation, graunt, or letters patentes: but that euerye suche persone and persones, bodies politike and corporate, their heires &amp; successours and assignes, and the heires, successoures, and assignes of euery of them, shall haue, holde, and enioy, all and euerye the same colleges, chappels, Chauntries, Manours, landes, Tenementes, Reuenues, Possessions, and Hereditamentes, and all and euerye other thing and things whatsoeuer, so by them had or obteined, by the assent, licence, confirmation, graunte, or letters Patentes of the sayde late kyng, or of the kynges Maiestie that now is, according to the woordes, sentences, fourme, effecte, meaning, and entent of the same lycences, confirmations, grauntes, and Letters Patentes: thys acte, or the sayde acte made in the sayd xxxvii. yere of the reigne of the said late kyng Henry the eight, or any clause, article, sentence, matter, or thing menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, expressed, or conteined in any of the same actes, to the contrary thereof in any wise not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:150873:36"/>
            <head>¶ An acte concerning the kyngs most gratious generall Pardone. ¶ The .xv. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He kynges moste Royal Maiestie right well percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hys louing subiects by many and sundry waies and meanes, to haue borne &amp; susteined the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures, charges, and businesse of warres, &amp; desen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of thys hys realme, aswel in the tyme of his most dere father kyng Henry the eight, as in his time and reigne, entending of hys clemēcie and pity to gratify hys sayd subiects with his gratious free and liberal pardon, according to hys kyngly power, trusting assuredly that his said subiectes will cōtinue hys louing &amp; assured obediēt subiects, &amp; hereafter in such sort obey hys hyghnesse lawes &amp; statutes, as to thē, and euery of thē of right apperteineth: is fully and resolutelye contented &amp; pleased, that it bee enacted by aucthoritie of thys present parlament, in maner &amp; fourme folowing, that is to say, that all and euerye of hys said subiects, aswell spirituall as temporall, of thys hys realme of Englande, Wales, the Isles of Iernesey and Garnesey, Barwicke, Caleis, Guisnes, Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Bulleyn, and Bull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>noys, and the marches of the same, the heires, successours, executours, and administratours of them and euery of thē, and all and singular bodies in any maner of wise corporate, Cities, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, Shires, Ridinges, Hundredes, Lathes, Wapentakes, Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Villages, and Tithings, and euery of them, and the successour and successoures of euerye of them, shalbe by the aucthoritie of thys present Parlamente, acquited, pardoned, released and discharged againste the kynges hyghenes, hys heires, successoures, and executours, and euerye of them, of all maner of Treasons, Heresies, Felonies, Robberies, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Contemptes, Trespasses, wronges, deceiptes, misdemeanours, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, penalties, and profites, summes of money, peines of death, pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes corporall and pecuniarie, and all other thinges, causes, quereles, su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, iudgementes, and executions, which may be, or can be by hys hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in anye wise, or by any meane pardoned, before, and vnto the xxv. daye of Decembre, in the yere of our Lord God a M.CCCCC.xlvii. Other then suche as hereafter in thys acte bee excepted or foreprised, in such maner and fourme, and vnto such times as they be excepted or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised in thys act: and other then such as the clauses or prouisos hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mentioned, doth extende vnto. And also the kinges hyghnesse is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contented and pleased, that it bee enacted by the aucthoritie of this present Parlament, that thys hys said free pardone shalbe as good and effectuall in the lawe, to euery of hys sayde subiectes, bodies corporate, and other before rehearsed, and to euerye of them, by the saide generall
<pb facs="tcp:150873:37"/> wordes before rehearsed in all thinges, which bee not hereafter in thys present act excepted or forprised, as the same pardon shoulde haue been, if all offences, contemptes, forfeitures, causes, matters, sutes, querelles, iudgementes, executions, penalties, and all other thinges not hereafter excepted, nor conteined in any clause of prouiso herafter mentioned, had been, particularly, singularly, specially, and plainely named, rehearsed, &amp; specified, and also pardoned by propre and expresse wordes and names, in their kyndes, natures, and qualities, by wordes and termes thereūto requisite, to haue ben put in, and expressed in thys present act of free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done: and that hys sayd subiectes, nor any of them, nor the heires, execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours or administratours of any of them, nor any of the said bodies cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, nor any other persons, bodies politike or corporat before named, or anye of them, bee, nor shalbe sued, vexed, or inquieted in their bodies, goodes, landes, or cattalles, for any maner matter, cause, contempt, mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour, forfeiture, trespasse, offence, or any other thing, suffred, doen or cōmitted against his hyghnes, his crown, dignitie, prerogatiue, lawe or statutes, but onely for suche matters, causes, and offences, as bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsed in the exceptions and clauses of prouiso, in thys present act her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after mentioned, in suche maner and fourme as in the same exceptiōs &amp; clauses of prouiso be mentioned, and for none other: any statute or statu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, lawes, customes, vses, or president heretofore had, made, or vsed, to the contrarye in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Also the kynges hyghnesse, of hys bounteous liberalitie, by auctoritie of thys present parlament, graunteth and freely geueth to euery of hys sayde subiectes, and to euerye of the said bodies corporate and other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearsed, and to euery of them, all suche goodes, cattalles, debtes, fines, issues, profites, amerciamentes, forfeitures and summes of money by anye of them forfeicted, which to hys hyghnes doe, or shoulde belong or appertain by reason of any offence, contēpt, trespasse, misdemeanour, matter, cause, or querele suffred, doen or committed by them, or anye of them, whiche be not hereafter foreprised or excepted in thys present act. And that all and euery the kynges sayde subiectes, and all and singuler bodies corporate, and other before rehearsed, maye by hym or themselfe, or by hys or their deputie or deputies, or by hys or their attorney, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torneyes, accordinge to the lawes of thys Realme, pleade and minister thys present act of free pardon for hys or their discharge, of, &amp; for euerye thing, that is by vertue of this present act pardoned, discharged, geuen, or graunted without any fee or other thing, in any wise payinge to anye person or persons, for writing, or entrie of the iudgement, or other cause cōcerning such plee, writing or entrie, but onely xii. d. to bee payed to the officer or clerke that shall entre the plee, matter or iudgemēt, for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of any of the partie so pleading the same: anye statute, or vse, to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, the kyngs hyghnesse is contented and pleased, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150873:37"/> it be enacted, by the aucthoritie of thys present parlament, that his sayd free pardone, by the general woordes before rehearsed, shalbe reputed, demed, and adiudged, allowed, and taken in all maner of courtes, &amp; els where, aswell in the woordes and clauses of exceptions and foreprises specified in thys present act, as in all and singuler other clauses, words, and sentences, mentioned and rehearsed in thys hys sayde free pardone most beneficially and auaileably, to all and singular hys saide subiectes, bodies corporate, and other before rehearsed, and to euery of thē, in all thinges ambiguous, or doubtfull, and moste strongly in Barre, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge against hys hyghnesse, hys heires, successoures, and executours, in euery thing, without any obstacle, challenge, or other delay, whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it shalbe, to be made, pleaded, obiected, or alleged by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> king our soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne lord, his heirs, successours, or executours, or by his, or any of their general attorney, or atturneys, or by any persone or persons, for hys hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghenes, or any of hys heires, successours, or executours.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, it is enacted by the kyng our Souereigne Lord, by aucthoritie of this present parlament, that yf any officer or clerke, of any of hys hyghnesse courtes, commonly called the kynges benche, Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, &amp; Common place, or of hys Excheker, or any other officer or clerke of any other court within thys realme, or in Wales, or other the kynges dominions aboue mentioned, at any tyme after the twentie daye of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary next comminge, which shalbe in the yere of our Lorde God a. M.CCCCC.xlvii. make out, or write out any maner writtes, or other pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cesse, or any extractes, sommons, or other preceptes, wherby anye of the sayde subiectes, or anie of the sayde bodies corporate, or other before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsed, or any of them, shalbe in any wise arrested, attached, distreined, sommoned, or otherwise vexed, inquieted, or grieued in his or theire bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, landes, tenementes, goodes, or cattalles, or in any of thē, for, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of any maner of thing pardoned or discharged, by vtue of this act of free pardone, he so offending, and therof lefully condēpned, shal yelde and paye for the recompence therof, to the partie so grieued or offended, treble damages, to bee accompted, as parcel of the damages and costes of the suite. And neuerthelesse, all and singular such writtes, processe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes and preceptes so to be made, for, or vpon any maner thing pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or discharged by thys presente acte of free pardone, shalbee vtterlye voide and of none effect.</p>
            <p>Excepted alwayes and foreprised out of thys general and free pardō, all and all maner of hyghe Treasons, petit Treason, and misprision of Treason, doen, committed, or perpetrated, in any of the parties beyonde the sea, and all and all maner of Treason, doen, or committed in anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, by any persone or persones, by any ouert deede, whereby any bodily hurt or harme shal come, or be doen to the kynges onely persone, and all suites, punishementes, executions, forfeictures and penalties, for or by reason or occasion of anye of the same Treasons, before excepted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150873:38"/>
            <p>And excepted all prepensed and voluntary murders, and also except al titles of actions, of <hi>Quare impedit,</hi> all rauishments, and withholding of the kyngs Wardes and Wardes landes, and the profites of the same at anye tyme growen to the kyngs handes, or to anye of hys noble proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitoures, and not yet discharged, all wastes of the kynges woodes, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in Parkes, Forestes, chases, and els where, and all summes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney graunted, or promised to be payed, by waye or meane of beneuolēce or contribution not payed and contented: and all and singuler debtes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then debtes growen vpon Recognisaunces, being alreadye forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for suertie of the peace, good abearing, or for none apparaunce at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny day or place. And excepted and forprised out of this pardon, all maner of accoumptes, and all actions, suites, and impetitions for the same, and all arrerages of accomptes and debtes due for the same. And also, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all homages, liueries, and reliefes, rentes, seruices, and arrerages of the same, not doen, or not paied. And also excepted al debtes, which wer due to the kyngs hyghnesse, or to the sayd late kyng of famous memory kyng Henry the eight, or to the late kyng Henry the vii. or to any person or persons, to the vse of the kyng our souereigne lord, or of hys saide fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or kyng Henry the vii. by anye condemnation, recognisaunce, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiō, or otherwise. And also excepted all and singuler forfeitures being due to our souereigne Lord the kyng, or to the sayde late kynge, by any penal statute or statutes, whiche be conuerted into the nature of debte, by iudgement, or by agreement of the offendour, and al forfeitures, and other penalties and profites, growen, or due by reason of any offence or acte committed or doen, contrary to any statute or statutes, or contrary to the common lawe, wherof any seisure is made, or any information is geuen in the kynges Excheker, or any suite there commensed, &amp; now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, and not yet determined: Or wherof the kynges hyghenesse, or his sayde father, by bill assigned, or otherwise, haue made any gift or as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signement, to any of the seruaunts of our said souereigne lord the kyng, or of hys said father, or to any other persone or persones.</p>
            <p>Also except and forprised out of thys free pardone, all and all maner of forgeing, counterfeycting, washing, and clipping of whatsoeuer moneye or coyne, currant in thys Realme, and the bringing into thys Realme of any false or counterfeict moneye or coigne, made, forged, or counterfeit out of this realme, and the vttering of any such false or counterfeict mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or coyne, had, made, done, or perpetrated, sithen the xxvii. day of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary last past, &amp; all &amp; all maner of offences, impetitions, punishements, forfeitures, peines of deathe, iudgementes, and execution for the same. And also, except and forprised out of thys free pardone, all and singular fines to be had, made, or payed, by reason or meane of anye alienation, had or made of any manours, landes, tenementes, or other hereditamē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes without licence, sithen the sayde xxvii. day of Ianuary. Also excepte &amp; forprised out of thys free pardon, all and all maner of manslaughters,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150873:38"/> Burgularies, roberies, of any persone or persones, in any house, or nere anye hygh waye, and wilful burning of houses, and wilful burninge of Barnes, in whiche Barnes any corne was, at the time of such burning, and all maner of rauishmentes of any woman against her will; all felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious takyng of any money or goodes, out of any churche or chappel, al and all maner of felonious taking of any horse, gelding, or mare, and all maner of piracies and offences vpon the Sea, had, done, committed, or perpetrated, sithen the first day of August last past: and all maner of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishementes, impeticions, forfeitures, peines of deathe, Iudgementes, and executions for the same. And excepte and forprised out of thys free pardon, all, &amp; all maner of intrusions, had, made, or doen, sithen the saide xxvii. day of Ianuary last past. And except and forprised out of this free pardone, all and all maner of deceytes and offences, of all and singular moniers, and other officers, ministers, &amp; workemen, of, or in any of the Mintes within thys realme, and all impetitions and punishementes for the same. And except and forprised out of thys free Pardone, all and all maner of decaying of any mesuage, cotage, or house, and the conuerting of landes from tillage vnto pasture, contrary to any statute, heretofore had or made. And excepte and forprised the issues, reuenues, &amp; profites of all and singular suche Mesuages, cotages, houses, and Landes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, arising, or growing, sithen the saide xxvii. daye of Ianuarye laste past. And except and forprised out of thys free pardone, all and singular collectours, or collectour of any Subsidie, fiftene, beneuolence, or contri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bution, and other persones whatsoeuer, that ought to be accomptaunt, and the heirs, executours, and administratours of euery of them, of, for, and concerninge all maner of debtes, accoumptes, and arrerages of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumptes, &amp; all maner of concelementes of customes and subsidies, and all maner of impetitions and suites for the same. And except &amp; forprised out of thys free pardon, all and singular persones and persone, being the ii. daye of Decembre, in the yere of our Lord God M.D.xlvii. prisoners or prisoner, in the tower of London, &amp; all and singular persons and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, which at any time, before the ii. day of Decēbre, did flie out of thys realme, into the parties beyond the sea, for anye treason, or misprision of treason. And excepte and forprised out of this free pardone, all issues, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and amerciaments, affered, taxed, set, extracted, or entred seuerally or perticularly, extending to the somme of an C.s. or aboue. And that al and singular other fines, aswel fines <hi>pro licentia concordandi</hi> as other, and all other issues and amerciamentes, aswell reall as other, which se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally or perticularly, extēd not to the same sōme of .C.s. whether they be totted or not totted, taken to the charge of the sherife, or not taken to his charge, extracted, or not extracted, whether they be torned into debt or not into debte, and not being leuied, nor receiued by any shirife or shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifes, bailife, ministers, or other officers, shalbe fully, clerely, and plainely pardoned, &amp; discharged against the king our souereigne lord, hys heirs
<pb facs="tcp:150873:39"/> and successours for euer, by thys present acte of free pardone.</p>
            <p>And bee it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforesayd, that in case it be obiected, to, or against any Sherif or Sherifes, or other accomptan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the kynges court of Escheker, or in anye other hys Courtes, that anye Sherife or Sherifes, other then officers accomptant, haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or taken any such fines, issues, or amerciaments, by thys present act pardoned and acquited: that then euery suche Sherif and Sherifes, &amp; other accomptantes shalbe discharged, released, pardoned, and acquited therof, by hys or their othe, without any further triall in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that thys present act of free pardone, nor anye thing therein conteined, in any wise extend to discharge, remit, or acquite, any persone and persones, for anye suche issues, fines, or amerciamentes, of one hūdred shillinges or vnder, as any Shirife heretofore haue accoūp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, before the Barones of the kynges Excheker, or els where, &amp; payed the same Issues, Fines, and Amerciamentes, vpon hys or their said ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpte, determined to the kyngs vse, and hath hys or their <hi>quietus est</hi> for the same.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, and bee it enacted, by the aucthoritie of thys present parlament, that all and euery persone and persones, which haue tended or ought to sue liuery out of the kyngs handes, of any Manours, lādes, tenementes and hereditamentes whatsoeuer they bee, shall sue hys or their liuerie and liueries, out of the kynges handes, of hys or their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, landes, tenementes, &amp; hereditamentes: any article, acte or actes, thing or thinges, in thys present acte of generall and free pardone, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised and specified, to the contrarye notwithstanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, &amp; bee it enacted by the aucthoritie aforesaide, that it shalbe lefull to all and euery clerke, and other officer of any of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Courtes, to awarde and make writtes of <hi>Capias vtlagatum,</hi> at the suite of the partie pleintife, to the entente to compel the defendaunt and defendauntes, to make aunswere to the plaintife, at whose suite he was outlawed. And that euery persone now being outlawed, shal sue a writ of <hi>Scire facias</hi> against the partie or parties, at whose suite he was outla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed before, hys pardone in that behalfe shalbe allowed to hym, that so is outlawed.</p>
            <trailer>❧ <hi>God saue the Kyng.</hi> ❧</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Excusum Londini, in aedibus Richardi Graftoni, Regii Impressoris.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Anno. M.D.xlviii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>